<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: meditation | Science & Fun - Jonathan Graehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/?tag=meditation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-11T23:34:57-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://graehl.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Graehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[graehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[about to get hurt? meditate.]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2011/04/07/about-to-get-hurt-meditate/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-07T18:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2011/04/07/about-to-get-hurt-meditate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 14px; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px;"><span style="border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 13px;">
</span></span><p>Researchers have<span> </span><a href="http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2011-04/wfub-dm033111.php" target="_blank" style="color: #2244bb;">shown</a><span> </span>that meditation produces a 40 percent reduction in pain intensity and a 57 percent reduction in pain unpleasantness.</p>
<p>Fifteen healthy volunteers (who had never meditated) attended four 20-minute classes to learn a meditation technique known as “focused attention.” This is a form of mindfulness meditation where people are taught to attend to the breath and let go of distracting thoughts and emotions.</p>
</blockquote>


<p>They actually caused people pain after the meditation (or non-meditation). Cool. </p>


<p></p>


<p>  Not that it makes any difference in the result, but I like when they can correlate brain scan differences with outcome differences:</p>

<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 14px; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px;"><span style="border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 13px;">
</span></span><p>meditation significantly reduced brain activity in the primary somatosensory cortex, an area that is crucially involved in creating the feeling of where and how intense a painful stimulus is.</p>
<p>The research also showed that meditation increased brain activity in areas including the anterior cingulate cortex, anterior insula and the orbito-frontal cortex, which shape how the brain builds an experience of pain from nerve signals from the body. The more these areas were activated by meditation, the more that pain was reduced.</p>
</blockquote>


<p>I didn't notice what, if anything, they did to control for placebo effects. They should also test whether just breathing deeply, without any long meditation practice, explains some of the effect.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vipassana meditation (part 3)]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2010/11/17/vipassana-meditation-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-17T11:01:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2010/11/17/vipassana-meditation-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="">part 1</a><br> <a href="">part 2</a></p>


<p></p>


<p>  <br> This covers my first Vipassana-like meditation, as described in chapter 5.</p>

<blockquote>
<a><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span> </span></span></a><a> </a>
<h3>
<a><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: medium;"> </span></a><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: medium;"><a href="http://www.urbandharma.org/udharma4/mpe5-6.html">Chapter 5</a></span>
</h3>
</blockquote>


<p> </p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><h3><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-size: small;"> </span></span></h3>
<p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">Seeing with wisdom means seeing things within the framework of our body/mind complex without prejudices or biases springing from our greed, hatred and delusion. Ordinarily when we watch the working of our mind/body complex, we tend to hide or ignore things which are not pleasant to us and to hold onto things which are pleasant. This is because our minds are generally influenced by our desires, resentment and delusion. Our ego, self or opinions get in our way and color our judgment.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>Obviously.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">When we mindfully watch our bodily sensations, we should not confuse them with mental formations, for bodily sensations can arise without anything to do with the mind. For instance, we sit comfortably. After a while, there can arise some uncomfortable feeling on our back or in our legs. Our mind immediately experiences that discomfort and forms numerous thoughts around the feeling. </span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>Agreed. Whatever I pay attention to, prompts thoughts.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">At that point, without trying to confuse the feeling with the mental formations, we should isolate the feeling as feeling and watch it mindfully. Feeling is one of the seven universal mental factors. </span></p>
</blockquote>


<p> </p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">The other six are contact, perception, mental formations, concentration, life force, and awareness.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>meaningless mumbo jumbo to me. needs explanation.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">At another time, we may have a certain emotion such as, resentment, fear, or lust. Then we should watch the emotion exactly as it is without trying to confuse it with anything else. When we bundle our form, feeling, perceptions, mental formations and consciousness up into one and try to watch all of them as feeling, we get confused, as we will not be able to see the source of feeling. If we simply dwell upon the feeling alone, ignoring other mental factors, our realization of truth becomes very difficult. </span></p>
</blockquote>


<p> </p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">We want to gain the insight into the experience of impermanence to over come our resentment;</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>huh? more undefined nonsense.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> our deeper knowledge of unhappiness overcomes our greed which causes our unhappiness; </span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>I'll stop being greedy if I realize it's causing my unhappiness. He appears to be claiming that I don't even realize when I'm unhappy. It's true that I sometimes don't think at all about how I feel.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">our realization of selflessness overcomes ignorance arising from the notion of self.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>nonsense. 'selflessness' hasn't even been defined. I have no idea what it is. For me, the 'notion of self' is just a fact. I'm a machine, distinct from other objects.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> We should see the mind and body separately first. Having comprehended them separately, we should see their essential interconnectedness.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>If they're not separable, then why try to understand them in isolation? It only makes sense to think about "mind" because we can't scan and model all the physical details of our own brain (and definitely not others').</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> As our insight becomes sharp, we become more and more aware of the fact that all the aggregates are cooperating to work together. None can exist without the other. We can see the real meaning of the famous metaphor of the blind man who has a healthy body to walk and the disabled person who has very good eyes to see. Neither of them alone can do much for himself. But when the disabled person climbs on the shoulders of the blind man, together they can travel and achieve their goals easily. Similarly, the body alone can do nothing for itself. It is like a log unable to move or do anything by itself except to become a subject of impermanence, decay and death. The mind itself can do nothing without the support of the body. When we mindfully watch both body and mind, we can see how many wonderful things they do together.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>My mind already coordinates quite well with my body. I'm not seeing any useful concrete advice, or evidence of advanced skill on the part of the uathor.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">As long as we are sitting in one place we may gain some degree of mindfulness. Going to a retreat and spending several days or several months watching our feelings, perceptions, countless thoughts and various states of consciousness may make us eventually calm and peaceful. </span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>Maybe. I wonder if I'll ever try this.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">Normally we do not have that much time to spend in one place meditating all the time. Therefore, we should find a way to apply our mindfulness to our daily life in order for us to be able to handle daily unforeseeable eventualities. </span></p>
</blockquote>


<p> </p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">What we face every day is unpredictable. Things happen due to multiple causes and conditions, </span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>true</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">as we are living in a conditional and impermanent world. </span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>huh? zero descriptive value.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">Mindfulness is our emergency kit, readily available at our service at any time. When we face a situation where we feel indignation, if we mindfully investigate our own mind, we will discover bitter truths in ourselves. That is we are selfish; we are egocentric; we are attached to our ego; we hold on to our opinions; we think we are right and everybody else is wrong; we are prejudices; we are biased; and at the bottom of all of this, we do not really love ourselves.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>I agree that in being frustrated when interacting with others, I can be saddened by the person I seem to be. If "ego" means "delusional self-beliefs", then I agree that we should try not to defend it. If "egocentric" means "not having a clear picture of, or really caring about, what's going on in others' heads", then I agree that this causes us to miscalculate. That I'm selfish is not a problem; I'm not going to give up trying to win just because it's sometimes frustrating.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> This discovery, though bitter, is a most rewarding experience. And in the long run, this discovery delivers us from deeply rooted psychological and spiritual suffering.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>Just knowing something about my nature doesn't necessarily free me from my nature.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">Mindfulness practice is the practice of one hundred percent honesty with ourselves.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>This sounds like my style. But I also allow myself to be optimistic (when calculating the exact odds of success is too much work), or else I'll never try anything hard. It can be valid to sacrifice precision at times, as long as the downside risk is roughly accounted for.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> When we watch our own mind and body, we notice certain things that are unpleasant to realize. As we do not like them, we try to reject them. What are the things we do not like? </span></p>
</blockquote>


<p> </p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">We do not like to detach ourselves from loved ones or to live with unloved ones.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>Nor should we.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> We include not only people, places and material things into our likes and dislikes, but opinions, ideas, beliefs and decisions as well.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>Yes, I feel pleased and displeased to varying degrees by everything in my mind.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> We do not like what naturally happens to us. We do not like, for instance, growing old, becoming sick, becoming weak or showing our age, for we have a great desire to preserve our appearance.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>As is wise.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> We do not like someone pointing out our faults, for we take great pride in ourselves.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>Except in the company of those I know value me fairly, it's true that I will irrationally defend myself because of status instinct. And probably I should, or else lose out to those who do. Nobody else is going to represent me in this way.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> We do not like someone to be wiser than we are, for we are deluded about ourselves. </span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>I love it, when they are on my side.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">These are but a few examples of our personal experience of greed, hatred and ignorance.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">When greed, hatred and ignorance reveal themselves in our daily lives, we use our mindfulness to track them down and comprehend their roots. The root of each of these mental states in within ourselves. If we do not, for instance, have the root of hatred, nobody can make us angry, for it is the root of our anger that reacts to somebody's actions or words or behavior.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>Even if it's possible, why would I want to be incapable of anger?</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> If we are mindful, we will diligently use our wisdom to look into our own mind. If we do not have hatred in us we will not be concerned when someone points out our shortcomings. Rather, we will be thankful to the person who draws our attention to our faults. We have to be extremely wise and mindful to thank the person who explicates our faults so we will be able to tread the upward path toward improving ourselves. We all have blind spots. The other person is our mirror for us to see our faults with wisdom. We should consider the person who shows our shortcomings as one who excavates a hidden treasure in us that we were unaware of. It is by knowing the existence of our deficiencies that we can improve ourselves. Improving ourselves is the unswerving path to the perfection which is our goal in life. Only by overcoming weaknesses can we cultivate noble qualities hidden deep down in our subconscious mind. Before we try to surmount our defects, we should what they are.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>1. are they correct? if so, believe it.<br> 2. are they harming your status?<br> 2a. then defuse it by thanking them and acting unconcerned for status (even if they're wrong)<br> 2b. fight their claim (even if they're right)</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">If we are sick, we must find out the cause of our sickness. Only then can we get treatment. If we pretend that we do not have sickness even though we are suffering, we will never get treatment. Similarly, if we think that we don't have these faults, we will never clear our spiritual path. If we are blind to our own flaws, we need someone to point them out to us. When they point out our faults, we should be grateful to them like the Venerable Sariputta, who said: "Even if a seven-year-old novice monk points out my mistakes, I will accept them with utmost respect for him."</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>Easy, if he never happened to agree with anyone's claim that he made a mistake.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"> Ven. Sariputta was an Arahant who was one hundred percent mindful and had no fault in him.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>Useless information.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">One who speaks with resentment cannot be mindful and is unable to express himself clearly. One who feels hurt while listening to harsh language may lose his mindfulness and not hear what the other person is really saying. We should speak mindfully and listen mindfully to be benefitted by talking and listening. </span></span></blockquote>


<p>I thought being mindful was just being aware of your feelings and 100% self-honest. So I could feel resentful and know it - even know why I feel resentful - and still be mindful. I could also communicate clearly while choosing to be harsh, but it's true that I should expect my target to bristle.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">When we listen and talk mindfully, our minds are free from greed, selfishness, hatred and delusion.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>If this is a substantive claim, I don't understand it. I don't see why my mind is free from such things just because I perceive them honestly and clearly.</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">Our goal is to reach the perfection of all the noble and wholesome qualities latent in our subconscious mind. This goal has five elements to it: Purification of mind, overcoming sorrow and lamentation, overcoming pain and grief, treading the right path leading to attainment of eternal peace, and attaining happiness by following that path.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>I'll summarize this as "reducing delusional beliefs, and freedom from the full weight of negative feelings". I don't think being fully content in the worst of external circumstances is really possible.</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">Once you sit, do not change the position again until the end of the time you determined at the beginning. Suppose you change your original position because it is uncomfortable, and assume another position. What happens after a while is that the new position becomes uncomfortable. Then you want another and after a while, it too becomes uncomfortable. So you may go on shifting, moving, changing one position to another the whole time you are on your mediation cushion and you may not gain a deep and meaningful level of concentration. Therefore, do not change your original position, no matter how painful it is.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>Seems like bad advice.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"><span> </span>If you have never meditated before, sit motionless not longer than twenty minutes.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>timer: <a href="http://www.berkeleymonastery.org/meditate.asp">http://www.berkeleymonastery.org/meditate.asp</a></p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"><span> </span>if you keep quiet without moving you body, focusing your entire undivided attention on the subject of your meditation, your mind settles down and begins to experience the bliss of meditation.</span></span></blockquote>


<p><br> I just tried 10 minutes after reading this far. I ended my meditation 5 seconds before the timer rang (my brain knows what 10 minutes is?).</p>


<p></p>


<p>  I don&rsquo;t avoid thoughts while meditating; I just try to not get emotionally agitated. Worries, plans, dissatisfactions, and concerns that came to mind had simple and easily reached explanations. My thoughts definitely don&rsquo;t need fixing. When my temper/defensiveness is aroused, I definitely become combative and rash, but that doesn&rsquo;t affect me normally, and I&rsquo;m not so sure that it&rsquo;s a terrible thing.<p></p>  I felt good. I adjusted my position until I was comfortable, then remained for about 9 minutes. I heard people talking nearby, but that doesn&rsquo;t distract me. I&rsquo;ll do it again. I like being awake and free of significant distractions, so my thoughts are slower and less reactive. I&rsquo;ve meditated in yoga class, but that context is somewhat distracting (I&rsquo;m excessively conscious of how my body feels, and the fact that I&rsquo;m in a class).<p></p>  Aside from rest and quiet-thinking-time, I can see meditation as a possible emotional self-regulation practice &ndash; maybe similar to what you&rsquo;d get by practicing controling some biofeedback indicator. I do feel something that could be described as being aware of different parts of my mind, especially the difference between what comes from my body&rsquo;s senses and what comes (mostly) unprompted by them. I don&rsquo;t feel any super bliss or &ldquo;self is an illusion&rdquo;.<p></p>  I don&rsquo;t feel transformed. Just relaxed. If I were more tired, a 10 minutes nap would probably be more relaxing. But I have more specific and pleasant memories of a meditation experience than a nap (where I sometimes remember a few disjointed seconds of sleep-thought).<p></p>  Also, instead of paying attention to my breath as a fixed point as was recommended, I took something more abstract &ndash; my mortality. I think that&rsquo;s the ultimate in true perspective.</p>

<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">To prepare for this attainment, we should keep our mind in the present moment. The present moment is changing so fast that the casual observer does not seem to notice its existence at all. Every moment is a moment of events and no moment passes by without noticing events taking place in that moment. Therefore, the moment we try to pay bare attention to is the present moment. Our mind goes through a series of events like a series of pictures passing through a projector. Some of these pictures are coming from our past experiences and others are our imaginations of things that we plan to do in the future.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">The mind can never be focused without a mental object. Therefore we must give our mind an object which is readily available every present moment. What is present every moment is our breath. The mind does not have to make a great effort to find the breath, for every moment the breath is flowing in and out through our nostrils. As our practice of insight meditation is taking place every waking moment, our mind finds it very easy to focus itself on the breath, for it is more conspicuous and constant than any other object.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>To get the bliss, focus on how you feel. That seems to be their recipe. Definitely a potential feedback loop. I didn't do this. I just paid attention to my thoughts/feelings and didn't spend more than a moment thinking about the referent of any one thought. Mostly I just thought about the thought itself, how it made me feel, and why I was having it (in simple, broad terms).</p>


<p></p>


<p>  I&rsquo;ll try this physical-present-focus-bliss recipe next time.<p></p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">After sitting in the manner explained earlier and having shared your loving-kindness with everybody</span></span></blockquote>


<p>I assume this means to remember a generalized love for all the people you can love. I don't think it was defined earlier.</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">take three deep breaths. After taking three deep breaths, breathe normally, letting your breath flow in and out freely, effortlessly and begin focusing your attention on the rims of your nostrils. Simply notice the feeling of breath going in and out. When one inhalation is complete and before exhaling begins, there is a brief pause. Notice it and notice the beginning of exhaling. When the exhalation is complete, there is another brief pause before inhaling begins. Notice this brief pause, too. This means that there are two brief pauses of breath--one at the end of inhaling, and the other at the end of exhaling. The two pauses occur in such a brief moment you may not be aware of their occurrence. But when you are mindful, you can notice them.</span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">Do not verbalize or conceptualize anything. Simply notice the in-coming and out-going breath without saying, "I breathe in", or "I breathe out." When you focus your attention on the breath ignore any thought, memory, sound, smell, taste, etc., and focus your attention exclusively on the breath, nothing else.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>sound easy</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">In spite of your concerted effort to keep the mind on your breathing, the mind may wander away. It may go to past experiences and suddenly you may find yourself remembering places you've visited, people you met, friends not seen for a long time, a book you read long ago, the taste of food you ate yesterday, and so on. As soon as you notice that you mind is no longer on your breath, mindfully bring it back to it and anchor it there.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>I don't generally have this problem, except a few times a year when I'm insomniac.</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">However, in a few moments you may be caught up again thinking how to pay your bills, to make a telephone call to you friend, write a letter to someone, do your laundry, buy your groceries, go to a party, plan your next vacation, and so forth.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>I do have such thoughts simmering below conscious notice (usually I'm too focused on my immediate task, but in meditating, they can pop up). It would be nice to temporarily disable them, as useful as they generally are.</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"><span> </span>As soon as you notice that your mind is not on your subject, bring it back mindfully. Following are some suggestions to help you gain the concentration necessary for the practice of mindfulness.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>I don't see what the hurry is. I'd rather understand why my mind is on the subject, then return to neutral. After all, I want honesty, insight, and clear thinking.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"><strong>1. Counting</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">In a situation like this, counting may help. The purpose of counting is simply to focus the mind on the breath. Once you mind is focused on the breath, give up counting. This is a device for gaining concentration. There are numerous ways of counting. Any counting should be done mentally.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p> </p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"><strong>2. Connecting</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">After inhaling do not wait to notice the brief pause before exhaling but connect the inhaling and exhaling, so you can notice both inhaling and exhaling as one continuous breath.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"><strong>3. Fixing</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">After joining inhaling and exhaling, fix your mind on the point where you feel you inhaling and exhaling breath touching. Inhale and exhale as on single breath moving in and out touching or rubbing the rims of your nostrils.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>redundant w/ 2. of course you're supposed to pay attention to how you feel in the moment.</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"><strong>4. Focus you mind like a carpenter</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">A carpenter draws a straight line on a board and that he wants to cut. Then he cuts the board with his handsaw along the straight line he drew. He does not look at the teeth of his saw as they move in and out of the board. Rather he focuses his entire attention on the line he drew so he can cut the board straight. Similarly keep your mind straight on the point where you feel the breath at the rims of your nostrils.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>redundant</p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span>
</span></span><p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;"><strong>5. Make you mind like a gate-keeper</strong></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #000000; font-family: Helvetica, Arial, sans-serif; font-size: small;">A gate-keeper does not take into account any detail of the people entering a house. All he does is notice people entering the house and leaving the house through the gate. Similarly, when you concentrate you should not take into account any detail of your experiences. Simply notice the feeling of your inhaling and exhaling breath as it goes in and out right at the rims of your nostrils.</span></p>
</blockquote>


<p>redundant</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">As you continue your practice you mind and body becomes so light that you may feel as if you are floating in the air or on water. You may even feel that your body is springing up into the sky. When the grossness of your in-and-out breathing has ceased, subtle in-and-out breathing arises. This very subtle breath is your objective focus of the mind. This is the sign of concentration. This first appearance of a sign-object will be replaced by more and more subtle sign-object.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>I guess you probably can form several levels of concepts in your brain for the various subjective noticing-breathing colors</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">But the breath becomes subtler and subtler as the sign develops. Because of this subtlety, you may not notice the presence of your breath. Don't get disappointed thinking that you lost your breath or that nothing is happening to your meditation practice. Don't worry. Be mindful and determined to bring your feeling of breath back to the rims of your nostrils. </span></span></blockquote>


<p>I disagree. You should do nothing. Maybe his recommendation is more likely to bring you the physical bliss, but if you want insight, I don't see why you should obsess over a fixed point.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">This is the time you should practice more vigorously, balancing your energy, faith, mindfulness, concentration and wisdom.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>mumbo jumbo</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">As you keep your mind focused on the rims of your nostrils, you will be able to notice the sign of the development of meditation. You will feel the pleasant sensation of sign. Different meditators feel this differently. It will be like a star, or a peg made of heartwood, or a long string, or a wreath of flowers, or a puff of smoke, or a cob-web, or a film of cloud, or a lotus flower, or the disc of the moon or the disc of the sun.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>Your spirit animal! I wonder how common such an association is, if not encouraged. Definitely I can close my eyes and at will recall visual imagery almost as in a dream.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">Earlier in your practice you had inhaling and exhaling as objects of meditation. Now you have the sign as the third object of meditation. When you focus your mind on this third object, your mind reaches a stage of concentration sufficient for your practice of insight meditation. This sign is strongly present at the rims of the nostrils. Master it and gain full control of it so that whenever you want, it should be available. Unite the mind with this sign which is available in the present moment and let the mind flow with every succeeding moment. As you pay bare attention to it, you will see the sign itself is changing every moment.<span> <br> </span></span></span></blockquote>


<p>It seems like he wants me to allow visual imagery to happen, and to not fix it to a single form. Good, that would be boring and maybe dangerous, like monitor burn-in :-)</p>


<p> </p>


<p> </p>


<p>Although I've tried meditation before, and will try it again, I recommend not reading "Mindfulness in Plain English". It's too much poor rhetoric, and doesn't at all live up to its grand promises. I will say that imagining being part of some "set of other people who've lived through exactly this emotional experience" is more soothing than I expected, so I appreciate Mindfulness and other books for recommending it.</p>


<p>Gurus are mostly full of it. Don't bother listening until you see evidence that they and their subjects are doing subtantially better than placebo. But if you like, go ahead and pick the placebo with the least costs. Maybe a life with no placebos at all is unnecessarily hard. After all, your skeptical purity is nothing to be proud of once you die (an inspiring example for others to live by? who cares - you're dead).</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vipassana meditation (part 2)]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2010/10/26/vipassana-meditation-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-26T14:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2010/10/26/vipassana-meditation-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="">part 1</a></p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"><strong>Attitude (ch 4)<br> </strong></span></span></blockquote>


<p> </p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">Within the last century, Western science and physics have made a startling discovery. We are part of the world we view. The very process of our observation changes the things we observe</span></span></blockquote>


<p>uh oh ...</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">Eastern science has recognized this basic principle for a very long time. The mind is a set of events, and the observer participates in those events every time he or she looks inward. Meditation is participatory observation. What you are looking at responds to the process of looking.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>You mean Eastern science has recognized the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncertainty_principle">Heisenberg uncertainty principle</a> that the product of the standard deviations of position and momentum of a particle is never less than half the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck%27s_constant">Planck constant</a>? AMAZING! No? Then you only embarrass yourself when you brag about how some thought that predates some scientific discovery is loosely analogous to it. Unless you're saying that some MAGIC source of wisdom caused the thought, that is now SCIENTIFICALLY PROVEN, why even mention it? So sad, the authority you claim for Eastern science. What happened to "don't trust us because of our meditation-expert authority - find out for yourself"?</p>


<p></p>


<p>  Anyway, how dense do you have to be to not grasp the difficulty of &ldquo;thinking about what you&rsquo;re thinking about right now&rdquo;? Clearly it&rsquo;s impossible to hold an exact model in your mind of what&rsquo;s in your mind. Great job, Eastern science. <p></p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">The following attitudes are essential to success in practice. Most of them have been presented before. But we bring them together again here as a series of rules for application.</span></span></blockquote>


<p> </p>


<blockquote>
<span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">1. Don't expect anything. Just sit back and see what happens. Treat the whole thing as an experiment. Take an active interest in the test itself. But don't get distracted by your expectations about results. For that matter, don't be anxious for any result whatsoever. Let the meditation move along at its own speed and in its own direction.</span></span><br>
</blockquote>


<p><br> The only way to introspect. Be quiet.</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">2. Don't strain: Don't force anything or make grand exaggerated efforts. Meditation is not aggressive. There is no violent striving. Just let your effort be relaxed and steady.<span> </span><p></p>  </span></span></blockquote>


<p>Same as above.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">3. Don't rush: There is no hurry, so take you time. Settle yourself on a cushion and sit as though you have a whole day. Anything really valuable takes time to develop. Patience, patience, patience.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>"Anything really valuable takes time to develop." Let's try that on for size ...</p>


<p>"Valuable" as in "scarce/costly": obviously, by definition. This is an uninteresting claim. But rhetorically people may believe the statement for other sense of "valuable" because of this interpretation. Sneaky rhetoric.</p>


<p>"Valuable" as in "useful": something can be novel, useful, and simple. But if extremely so, then you expect it to be widely circulated soon after discovery. And this is what we see: the technique of measuring volume of a solid by displaced water (Eureka indeed), randomly sampling from random samples (bootstrap resampling), "hold your breath and count to ten" (instead of starting a fight) etc. are quickly adopted. So, yes and no. The most valuable tools more than pay for the effort of becoming familiar with them. This is the bar Vipassana has to pass.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">4. Don't cling to anything and don't reject anything: Let come what comes and accommodate yourself to that, whatever it is. If good mental images arise, that is fine. If bad mental images arise, that is fine, too. Look on all of it as equal and make yourself comfortable with whatever happens. Don't fight with what you experience, just observe it all mindfully.<br> </span></span></blockquote>


<p>Agreed. You can't possibly sense what your mind does associatively and automatically if you're screaming at it.</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">5. Let go: Learn to flow with all the changes that come up. Loosen up and relax.<p></p>  6. Accept everything that arises: Accept your feelings, even the ones you wish you did not have. Accept your experiences, even the ones you hate. Don't condemn yourself for having human flaws and failings. Learn to see all the phenomena in the mind as being perfectly natural and understandable. Try to exercise a disinterested acceptance at all times and with respect to everything you experience.<p></p>  7. Be gentle with yourself: Be kind to yourself. You may not be perfect, but you are all you've got to work with. The process of becoming who you will be begins first with the total acceptance of who you are.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>Extremely redundant with what I've already agreed to above.</p>


<p></p>


<p></p>

<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">8. Investigate yourself: Question everything. Take nothing for granted. Don't believe anything because it sounds wise and pious and some holy men said it. See for yourself. </span></span></blockquote>


<p>Of course.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">That does not mean that you should be cynical, impudent or irreverent. </span></span></blockquote>


<p>Because he hates it when you question his teachings :)</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">It means you should be empirical. Subject all statements to the actual test of your experience and let the results be your guide to truth. Insight meditation evolves out of an inner longing to wake up to what is real and to gain liberating insight to the true structure of existence. The entire practice hinges upon this desire to be awake to the truth. Without it, the practice is superficial.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>Agree. It's necessary, but not sufficient, to want the truth in order to find it.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">9. View all problems as challenges: Look upon negatives that arise as opportunities to learn and to grow. Don't run from them, condemn yourself or bear your burden in saintly silence. You have a problem? Great. More grist for the mill. Rejoice, dive in and investigate.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>For some reason I don't consider such perspective-change mental illusions to be intellectually unhygienic. I'm okay with positive thinking, mental dis-integration (compartmentalization), and hypocrisy to the extent that it works (leads to eventually-true belief). I'm just skeptical that any particular "instead of thinking of X as X, think of it as Y, even if that's not exactly true" admonition is feasible or effective. "Challenge" does seem like a winning frame of mind, though.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">10. Don't ponder: You don't need to figure everything out. Discursive thinking won't free you from the trap. In mediation, the mind is purified naturally by mindfulness, by wordless bare attention. Habitual deliberation is not necessary to eliminate those things that are keeping you in bondage. All that is necessary is a clear, non-conceptual perception of what they are and how they work. That alone is sufficient to dissolve them. Concepts and reasoning just get in the way. Don't think. See.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>I don't know. I'll try it. I think the risk of reasoning is that you'll make salient other problematic thoughts/feelings. It does seem to conflict with awareness of natural thinking processes if you're always sidetracking things.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">11. Don't dwell upon contrasts: Differences do exist between people, but dwelling upon then is a dangerous process. Unless carefully handled, it leads directly to egotism. Ordinary human thinking is full of greed, jealousy and pride. A man seeing another man on the street may immediately think, "He is better looking than I am." The instant result is envy or shame. A girl seeing another girl may think, "I am prettier than she is." The instant result is pride. This sort of comparison is a mental habit, and it leads directly to ill feeling of one sort or another: greed, envy, pride, jealousy, hatred. It is an unskillful mental state, but we do it all the time. We compare our looks with others, our success, our accomplishments, our wealth, possessions, or I.Q. and all these lead to the same place--estrangement, barriers between people, and ill feeling.<p></p>  The meditator's job is to cancel this unskillful habit by examining it thoroughly, and then replacing it with another. Rather than noticing the differences between self and others, the meditator trains himself to notice similarities. He centers his attention on those factors that are universal to all life, things that will move him closer to others. Thus his comparison, if any, leads to feelings of kinship rather than feelings of estrangement.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>I have noticed that emphasizing in my mind what I have in common with a group of people helps me enjoy spending time with them. However, I don't think it makes sense to hide from true comparisons. I don't think justified and accurate pride or humility is harmful (except socially, if you advertise it indiscriminately). I see he says "unless carefully handled" and "don't dwell", so I'll consider this a point of possible agreement.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">Breathing is a universal process. All vertebrates breathe in essentially the same manner. All living things exchange gasses with their environment in some way or other. This is one of the reasons that breathing is chosen as the focus of meditation.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>Stupid reason, except I guess that automatic breathing is indeed regulated by part of the brain. Though I can't rule out that it's helpful to choose breathing in particular, I'd like to hear a better case than this. Note that it's dangerous to let people suggest crazy ideas machine-gun style and then try to evaluate each as though it might be true; you eventually slip up and make the mistake of believing something you never should have focused on (see <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/19m/privileging_the_hypothesis/">Privileging the Hypothesis</a>).</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">the meditator is advised to explore the process of his own breathing as a vehicle for realizing his own inherent connectedness with the rest of life. This does not mean that we shut our eyes to all the differences around us. Differences exist. It means simply that we de-emphasize contrasts and emphasize the universal factors.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>Weird. Seems motivated by the silly 'all evil is due to egotism' belief in Buddhism, so unlikely to be true. But I'll give it a shot.</p>


<blockquote><span style="border-collapse: separate; color: #000000; font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"><span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;">The recommended procedure is as follows:<p></p>  When the meditator perceives any sensory object, he is not to dwell upon it in the ordinary egotistical way. He should rather examine the very process of perception itself. He should watch the feelings that arise and the mental activities that follow. He should note the changes that occur in his own consciousness as a result. In watching all these phenomena, the meditator must be aware of the universality of what he is seeing. That initial perception will spark pleasant, unpleasant or neutral feelings. That is a universal phenomenon. It occurs in the mind of others just as it does in his, and he should see that clearly. Following these feelings various reactions may arise. He may feel greed, lust, or jealousy. He may feel fear, worry, restlessness or boredom. These reactions are universal. He simple notes them and then generalizes. He should realize that these reactions are normal human responses and can arise in anybody.<span> </span><p></p>  The practice of this style of comparison may feel forced and artificial at first, but it is no less natural than what we ordinarily do. It is merely unfamiliar. With practice, this habit pattern replaces our normal habit of egoistic comparing and feels far more natural in the long run. We become very understanding people as a result. we no longer get upset by the failings of others. We progress toward harmony with all life.</span></span></blockquote>


<p>Sounds nice. But I'd actually like to do the opposite - to become more cognizant of the fact that others are NOT like me in their thinking (they don't know what I know, etc.) - because I know I sometimes do a poor job of communicating when I don't model that well. I guess "we're all BASICALLY the same" doesn't conflict with that more specific modeling of others' knowledge/goals/capabilities, and might be a nice anchor to attach fellow-feeling to. I also know that it can be great fun to laugh at the failings of others with friends, but I suppose all mirth won't cease just because I regularly stoke a generalized empathy.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vipassana meditation (part 1)]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2010/10/26/vipassana-meditation-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-26T13:56:14-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2010/10/26/vipassana-meditation-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<pre><code>  I've started reading &lt;a href="http://www.urbandharma.org/udharma4/"&gt;Mindfulness in Plain English&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  My motivation in investigating any sort of Buddhist meditation is that, although I'm pretty detached already, I think I could be just as effective in the goals that you're supposed to not be "attached" to, with a quieter and more pleasurable internal life. I already think pretty hard about what's going on in my mind, and already try to form true, rather than comforting or self-serving, beliefs. I also already enjoy meditation or napping after enough physical exertion to involve me more in the immediate physical sensation rather than higher level goals, strivings, doubts, and worries in my life. I've heard enough mild recommendations from other intelligent folks that I'm open to the possibility that learning some existing meditation techniques might be more efficient than what comes naturally to me. I also doubt that I would have the desire to spend time regularly meditating unless I believed that it were better than the same amount of time exercising or sleeping, so I'm hoping to find some evidence of that.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  My impression of Buddhists is that they want to permanently dissociate from their ego (from being afraid of states of mind, of things and people that they're anchored to), and meditation is a means to this end. Perhaps you can still behave normally (as if you care), but you want the ability to not care, to not be prevented from seeing reality as it is by your fear of what you might lose, or delusional expectation or obsessive fantasy of what you desire. I think that some Buddhists respond to real threats with extreme pacifism, which is tempting given the rewards they've learned from a sort of inwardly-directed pacifism, but stupid - not caring only works against excessive worry and affect in your own mind, not actual mortal conflicts with nature and other people.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;What Meditation Is (ch 3)&lt;br&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; I won't bother commenting on the first two chapters, since they were just long-winded introduction (useful for people who have never heard of meditaiton, perhaps).&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  paraphrased:&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;Different practices that have been called 'meditation':&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Mere concentration exercises (focus thoughts in one area), which can result in calm/peace if what's concentrated on is simple and nonthreatening.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  1. Judeo-Christian prayer and contemplation.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  2. Yogic (Hindu) meditation - repeat a syllable, or focus on an object. Moving to complex focuses (imagined energy flows in body, chants, images) later.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  3. Zen (Buddhist) meditation - either focus only on the experience of sitting, or try to solve impossible riddles. Both often under physical duress at a meditation retreat. Eventually you crack (in a good way, you hope).&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  4. Tantra (also Buddhist) - pretend you're one of the Tantric gods. Once you believe it, you're free to identify (or not) with yourself.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  5. Vipassana (also Buddhist) - become more sensitive to your own mind. Pay attention and look for real insight. Most people don't realize it's possible to *really* pay attention. It may take them years of training to be able to do it.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;/blockquote&gt; (end paraphrase)&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  If I want a concentration exercise, I'll do something better than stare at a rock. I'll create music. I'll lift weights. I'll practice my skill in some sport or performance activity. I'll program computers for money. I'll play &lt;a href="http://brainworkshop.sourceforge.net/"&gt;Dual N-Back&lt;/a&gt;. I'll think about my plans and beliefs. So I'm hoping for something more out of meditation than the opportunity to expend effort focusing my attention on something. I already focus my attention intentionally; I just do it on things that also have some other value to me.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;Through the process of mindfulness, we slowly become aware of what we really are down below the ego image. We wake up to what life really is. It is not just a parade of ups and downs, lollipops and smacks on the wrist. That is an illusion. Life has a much deeper texture than that if we bother to look, and if we look in the right way.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; The author breaks his "in Plain English" pledge already with "ego image". I presume he means the way we signal about ourselves to others for our profit, which necessarily involves rehearsing and self-deception (people are too good at detecting conscious lies and acting, so social confidence depends on hypocrisy and delusion).&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;Vipassana is a form of mental training that will teach you to experience the world in an entirely new way. You will learn for the first time what is truly happening to you, around you and within you. It is a process of self discovery, a participatory investigation in which you observe your own experiences while participating in them, and as they occur.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; I can't wait. What is it? I want it :)&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;"I want to apprehend the true and deepest qualities of life, and I don't want to just accept somebody else's explanation. I want to see it for myself." If you pursue your meditation practice with this attitude, you will succeed.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; That he makes this promise is nice, because I can be justifiably even more angry than usual if he turns out to have wasted my time. On the other hand, this is no different than other religions' empty promises that "if you ask God with a pure heart and good intent, the truth of this religion will be impressed upon you".&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;'Vipassana Bhavana' means the cultivation of the mind, aimed at seeing in a special way that leads to insight and to full understanding.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Ok, but what is it, specifically?&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;In Vipassana mediation we cultivate this special way of seeing life.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; I don't think 'this' is merited since you haven't described it yet. You haven't convinced me that there's something real behind the words you're using.&lt;br&gt; &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt; We train ourselves to see reality exactly as it is, and we call this special mode of perception 'mindfulness.' This process of mindfulness is really quite different from what we usually do. We usually do not look into what is really there in front of us. We see life through a screen of thoughts and concepts, and we mistake those mental objects for the reality. We get so caught up in this endless thought stream that reality flows by unnoticed. We spend our time engrossed in activity, caught up in an eternal pursuit of pleasure and gratification and an eternal flight from pain and unpleasantness. We spend all of our energies trying to make ourselves feel better, trying to bury our fears. We are endlessly seeking security. Meanwhile, the world of real experience flows by untouched and untasted. In Vipassana meditation we train ourselves to ignore the constant impulses to be more comfortable, and we dive into the reality instead.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;  I don't agree that my perception is wrong. My attention is a limited resource; I sometimes benefit from not seeing the texture of the asphalt on the road. I'm open to trying new modes of perception. I agree that we spend a lot of effort seeking social validation and other forms of pleasure. I've also always been sympathetic to the idea that there's some value in really apprehending reality in an unbiased way, which certainly means disregarding which belief brings the most comfort.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;When you relax your driving desire for comfort, real fulfillment arises. When you drop your hectic pursuit of gratification, the real beauty of life comes out. When you seek to know the reality without illusion, complete with all its pain and danger, that is when real freedom and security are yours. This is not some doctrine we are trying to drill into you. This is an observable reality, a thing you can and should see for yourself.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; I expect that a feeling of relief arises. Nothing more. But I will see for myself.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;Gotama the Buddha was a highly unorthodox individual and real anti-traditionalist. He did not offer his teaching as a set of dogmas, but rather as a set of propositions for each individual to investigate for himself. His invitation to one and all was 'Come and See'. One of the things he said to his followers was "Place no head above your own". By this he meant, don't accept somebody else's word. See for yourself.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; This would be embarrassing if it were not so. It's the only reason I give your ideas my time.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;From the Buddhist point of view, we human beings live in a very peculiar fashion. We view impermanent things as permanent, though everything is changing all around us. The process of change is constant and eternal. As you read these words, your body is aging. But you pay no attention to that. The book in you hand is decaying. The print is fading and the pages are becoming brittle. The walls around you are aging. The molecules within those walls are vibrating at an enormous rate, and everything is shifting, going to pieces and dissolving slowly. You pay no attention to that, either. Then one day you look around you. Your body is wrinkled and squeaky and you hurt. The book is a yellowed, useless lump; the building is caving in. So you pine for lost youth and you cry when the possessions are gone. Where does this pain come from? It comes from your own inattention. You failed to look closely at life. You failed to observe the constantly shifting flow of the world as it went by. You set up a collection of mental constructions, 'me', 'the book', 'the building', and you assume that they would endure forever. They never do. But you can tune into the constantly ongoing change. You can learn to perceive your life as an ever- flowing movement, a thing of great beauty like a dance or symphony. You can learn to take joy in the perpetual passing away of all phenomena. You can learn to live with the flow of existence rather than running perpetually against the grain.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; This seems crazy to me. I'm aware that I'm going to die; none of the other stuff about molecules vibrating or peeling off from the walls or from my body matters at all. Sounds like emotional nonsense.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;Our human perceptual habits are remarkably stupid in some ways. We tune out 99% of all the sensory stimuli we actually receive, and we solidify the remainder into discrete mental objects. Then we react to those mental objects in programmed habitual ways. An example: There you are, sitting alone in the stillness of a peaceful night. A dog barks in the distance. The perception itself is indescribably beautiful if you bother to examine it. Up out of that sea of silence come surging waves of sonic vibration. You start to hear the lovely complex patterns, and they are turned into scintillating electronic stimulations within the nervous system. The process is beautiful and fulfilling in itself. We humans tend to ignore it totally. Instead, we solidify that perception into a mental object. We paste a mental picture on it and we launch into a series of emotional and conceptual reactions to it. "There is that dog again. He is always barking at night. What a nuisance. Every night he is a real bother. Somebody should do something. Maybe I should call a cop. No, a dog catcher. So, I'll call the pound. No, maybe I'll just write a real nasty letter to the guy who owns that dog. No, too much trouble. I'll just get an ear plug." They are just perceptual and mental habits. You learn to respond this way as a child by copying the perceptual habits of those around you. These perceptual responses are not inherent in the structure of the nervous system. The circuits are there. But this is not the only way that our mental machinery can be used. That which has been learned can be unlearned. The first step is to realize what you are doing, as you are doing it, and stand back and quietly watch.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Okay, so you can reexamine things. You can even stare at a face until it becomes not a face, but a set of features. Sounds like a fun game. But I disagree that the way I think now is remarkably stupid.&lt;br&gt; &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;The cause of suffering is that desire- aversion syndrome which we spoke of earlier. Up pops a perception. It could be anything--a beautiful girl, a handsome guy, speed boat, thug with a gun, truck bearing down on you, anything. Whatever it is, the very next thing we do is to react to the stimulus with a feeling about it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; It sounds like being a Buddhist is about taking a time-out from trying. That sounds nice. But there's also a time to care and to try. It's possible that by taking some time not trying or caring, I'll learn something about my mental habits and make some improvement that will help me succeed at trying. Or maybe I'll just be less stressed, but stop trying. I doubt that's a big risk, though.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;Take worry. We worry a lot. Worry itself is the problem. Worry is a process. It has steps. Anxiety is not just a state of existence but a procedure. What you've got to do is to look at the very beginning of that procedure, those initial stages before the process has built up a head of steam. The very first link of the worry chain is the grasping/rejecting reaction. As soon as some phenomenon pops into the mind, we try mentally to grab onto it or push it away.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; I don't think grabbing onto a good feeling in your mind is something to worry about, unless it's via a dangerous drug. But pushing away and avoiding a feeling (basically overriding it with disapproval from another part of your mind, based on the fact that the feeling is unwelcome in pursuing some strong goal-desire) does seem truth-destroying and stress-inducing.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;Vipassana meditation teaches us how to scrutinize our own perceptual process with great precision. We learn to watch the arising of thought and perception with a feeling of serene detachment. We learn to view our own reactions to stimuli with calm and clarity. We begin to see ourselves reacting without getting caught up in the reactions themselves. The obsessive nature of thought slowly dies. We can still get married. We can still step out of the path of the truck. But we don't need to go through hell over either one.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Yes, I know this would be nice. I want to see things more clearly, and not suffer from internal emotional turmoil. Can you please describe how to do this? This is a painfully long preface.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;Along with this new reality goes a new view of the most central aspect of reality: 'me'. A close inspection reveals that we have done the same thing to 'me' that we have done to all other perceptions. We have taken a flowing vortex of thought, feeling and sensation and we have solidified that into a mental construct. Then we have stuck a label onto it, 'me'. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; I can't imagine how stupid you would have to be to not have a word/concept for 'me'.&lt;br&gt; &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;And forever after, we treat it as if it were a static and enduring entity. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; I've always been open to the possibility that I will change.&lt;br&gt; &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;We view it as a thing separate from all other things. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Here's what I think: I am definitely separate from all other things. My 'I' concept is not a faithful representation of what I am, but I'm eager to learn more about myself. I'm also eager to change in ways that get me more of what I presently value. I have no fear at all that I will stop existing because I, or my 'I' concept, change. I know I'm going to die. Where I drift before that happens had better be marvelous than in some deluded "I always stayed true to myself" rut.&lt;br&gt; &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;We pinch ourselves off from the rest of that process of eternal change which is the universe. And than we grieve over how lonely we feel. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; While it's true I feel lonely and value very highly deep mutual understanding and communication with a friend, I reject your claim that this is because I have a concept for 'me'.&lt;br&gt; &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;We ignore our inherent connectedness to all other beings and we decide that 'I' have to get more for 'me'; then we marvel at how greedy and insensitive human beings are. And on it goes. Every evil deed, every example of heartlessness in the world stems directly from this false sense of 'me' as distinct from all else that is out there.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Evil deeds are the result of natural human conflict, of the fact that it's often possible to profit at another man's expense, not because a 'me' concept prevents us from thinking 'when I harm any being, I'm harming the all-beings I'm a part of'. Maybe it feels good to think this, but I'm here for insight, not bullshit.&lt;br&gt; &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;These are all major insights, of course. Each one is a deep- reaching understanding of one of the fundamental issues of human existence. They do not occur quickly, nor without considerable effort. But the payoff is big. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; I wish you could make a reasonable case for the claims you've made, instead of making such extravagant promises of reward after years of commitment, which by the way will certainly bias my thinking if I foolishly choose to so commit.&lt;br&gt; &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;They lead to a total transformation of your life. Every second of your existence thereafter is changed. The meditator who pushes all the way down this track achieves perfect mental health, a pure love for all that lives and complete cessation of suffering. That is not small goal. But you don't have to go all the way to reap benefits. They start right away and they pile up over the years.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Good, so you're still enticing me with the promise that you're going to explain something that's testable and will immediately give me some abilities or pleasure I didn't have before. I guess I can keep reading.&lt;br&gt; &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;span style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: Times New Roman; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px; font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-family: Helvetica,Arial,sans-serif;"&gt;In the practice of mediation you become sensitive to the actual experience of living, to how things feel. You do not sit around developing subtle and aesthetic thoughts about living. You live. Vipassana meditation more than anything else is learning to live.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; Okay, but what is it?
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
