<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: history | Science & Fun - Jonathan Graehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/tag/history/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-05T16:39:51-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://graehl.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Graehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[graehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[modern art conspiracy]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2012/05/31/modern-art-conspiracy/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-31T11:57:59-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2012/05/31/modern-art-conspiracy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>CIA's International Organisations Division promoted U.S. modern art, presumably so we'd seem cooler than the commies.</div>


<div> </div>


<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;"> <blockquote style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 30px; padding: 10px 0px 0px 20px; font-size: 14px; line-height: 20.46666717529297px; color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Georgia,serif; text-align: left; background-color: rgb(224,224,224);">"We wanted to unite all the people who were writers, who were musicians, who were artists, to demonstrate that the West and the United States was devoted to freedom of expression and to intellectual achievement, without any rigid barriers as to what you must write, and what you must say, and what you must do, and what you must paint, which was what was going on in the Soviet Union. I think it was the most important division that the agency had, and I think that it played an enormous role in the Cold War." </blockquote> <blockquote style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 30px; padding: 10px 0px 0px 20px; font-size: 14px; line-height: 20.46666717529297px; color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Georgia,serif; text-align: left; background-color: rgb(224,224,224);">He confirmed that his division had acted secretly because of the public hostility to the avant-garde: "It was very difficult to get Congress to go along with some of the things we wanted to do - send art abroad, send symphonies abroad, publish magazines abroad. That's one of the reasons it had to be done covertly. It had to be a secret. In order to encourage openness we had to be secret." </blockquote> <blockquote style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 30px; padding: 10px 0px 0px 20px; font-size: 14px; line-height: 20.46666717529297px; color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Georgia,serif; text-align: left; background-color: rgb(224,224,224);">If this meant playing pope to this century's Michelangelos, well, all the better: "It takes a pope or somebody with a lot of money to recognise art and to support it," Mr Braden said. "And after many centuries people say, 'Oh look! the Sistine Chapel, the most beautiful creation on Earth!' It's a problem that civilisation has faced ever since the first artist and the first millionaire or pope who supported him. And yet if it hadn't been for the multi-millionaires or the popes, we wouldn't have had the art." </blockquote> </blockquote>


<p></p>


<div><a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/modern-art-was-cia-weapon-1578808.html">via</a></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
