<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Science & Fun - Jonathan Graehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/tag/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-05T18:19:42-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://graehl.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Graehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[graehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Among Others, The Name of the Wind]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2012/09/08/among-others-the-name-of-the-wind/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-08T12:53:24-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2012/09/08/among-others-the-name-of-the-wind</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>excellent: <a href="http://io9.com/5922140/ask-jo-walton-anything-you-want-about-among-others" target="_blank">Among Others</a> (Jo Walton) &ndash; except for a boring page of &ldquo;begats&rdquo;, and a too-easy climax nearly flawless. Smart author. The story features love of science fiction novels, and is so more rewarding to those who know the books referred to (it won the Hugo award partly on that strength). If you haven&rsquo;t read much science fiction, this is probably merely a good book. I didn&rsquo;t like how most of the nice observations offered by the heroine in her diary get shoved in my face a 2nd or 3rd time. I&rsquo;ll chalk that up to poor editing and/or forgetfulness by the diarist (or really, the author).<p></p></p>

<div>good: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Name_of_the_Wind">The Name of the Wind</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Wise_Man's_Fear">The Wise Man's Fear</a> (Rothfuss) - high status, magical bad-ass hero who's great at everything. Usual happy childhood brought low =&gt; scrappy beggar child =&gt; school soap opera =&gt; court politics =&gt; bandit hunting adventure =&gt; faerie idyll =&gt; secret asian martial arts training montage - in other words, covering most of the standard fantasy bases. Positives: bad ass hero portrayed convincingly by intelligent author. Negatives: too much time spent having others talk about how awesome the hero is, obnoxious love interest, overblown prose moments, and apparently our hero has been chewing male birth control herbs this whole time, we find out toward the end of the second book. I'm looking forward to the third (final?) tome.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cloud Atlas]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2011/12/01/cloud-atlas-tags-books-reviews/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-01T10:39:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2011/12/01/cloud-atlas-tags-books-reviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cloud_Atlas_(novel)">Cloud Atlas</a> is a moving and clever book. The blurbs on the back say "postmodern" but the only thing too-clever about it is the narrative structure, which I fully enjoyed. There's some Huck-Finn-annoying dialect, but it didn't bother me as much as usual.</p>


<p></p>


<div>I was surprised to read there's a film adaptation coming out next year. There's no way all of the plot will fit in a single film, but I look forward to watching it.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[entertainment]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2011/11/06/entertainment/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-06T08:35:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2011/11/06/entertainment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div><strong>TV:</strong></div>


<p>The Big Bang Theory - watched it all in the past 3 weeks. Sheldon grew on me.</p>


<p>The Office - still good.</p>


<p>The Boss - excellent acting. Sexy and interesting in the way The Wire was for its first 1.5 seasons.</p>


<div><strong>Music:</strong></div>


<div>
<br>Sufjan Stevens - "John Wayne Gacy, Jr." "The Seer's Tower" "To Be Alone with You", "For the Widows in Paradise, for the Fatherless in Ypsilanti", "Sister Winter" - all excellent</div>


<p></p>


<div><strong>Books: </strong></div>


<p></p>


<div>Stories of Your Life And Others (Ted Chiang) - fantastic.</div>


<p></p>


<div>REAMDE (Neal Stephenson) - diverting. Crichton-like. Too many bad-ass, cool characters. Hard to believe or care about most of it. Too long. Still worth reading.</div>


<p></p>


<div><strong>Movies:</strong></div>


<p></p>


<div>Beginners - similar artsy-emo lead as 500 days of summer, but more effectively brooding/poetic.</div>


<p></p>


<div>Crazy Stupid Love - in spite of a cheesy closing act (not quite Mrs. Doubtfire - painful, but bad), really funny</div>


<div>
<br>Margin Call - entertaining. Good acting except for the always-boring Demi Moore. I didn't care at all for the (Kevin Spacey) moral maybe-I'll-be-a-hero hand-wringing. I loved the soundtrack+trading-calls montage at the climax.</div>


<div>
<br>The Secret In Their Eyes - fantastic.</div>


<p></p>


<div>Midnight in Paris - good</div>


<p></p>


<div>Whatever Works - good</div>


<div>
<br>X-Men First Class - acceptable. better than the previous disaster.</div>


<div>
<br>Captain America (The First Avenger) - vapid but pretty. Felt like they ran out of money or ended up throwing out scenes - disjointed.</div>


<div>
<br>The Best of Youth (La meglio gioventù) - very good</div>


<p></p>


<div>Capturing the Friedmans - documentary. not recommended. ambiguous mix of overzealous/retarded community+law enforcement witch-hunt of actual creepy pedophile father. may interest people who aren't already familiar with witch-hunts.</div>


<p></p>


<div>Lilya 4-ever - good. a bit slow.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[misc. reviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2010/11/15/misc-reviews/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-15T13:41:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2010/11/15/misc-reviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>poor: dexter (current season only; first season and lithgow season were great), <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0944835/">salt</a>, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1386588/">the other guys</a>, <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1001526/">megamind</a>, twilight 2+3 (movies; 3 is one of the worst movies I've seen)</p>


<p>decent: house, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Hundred-Thousand-Kingdoms-Inheritance-Trilogy/dp/0316043915">the hundred thousand kingdoms</a> (female get-sexed-by-gods fantasy), <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Perdido-Street-Station-China-Mieville/dp/0345459407">perdido street station</a> (cleverly atmospheric but tedious), <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1099212/">twilight 1</a> (movie), remember me (loved the final school scene, hated the hit-by-bus ending. also, female lead was weakly acted)</p>


<p>good: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kimi_ni_Todoke">kimi ni todoke</a> (anime. in the extremely pure-hearted young romance subgenre. some very pretty moments amidst the formulaic cuteness), <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1091722/">adventureland</a> and <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0829576/">kristen stewart</a> (she's excellent at emoting desire for a man, and she doesn't overact) </p>


<p>great: <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm1500155/">robert pattinson</a> (even though he's been in only mediocre films so far), <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1399683/">winter's bone</a> (fantastic writing, casting, directing, and acting. final scene was devastating; take out the overdone "are u gonna leave us?" schmaltz and it's perfect.) loosely, it's a more female-centric version of <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1313092/">animal kingdom</a>, and nearly as good.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
