<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: psychology | Science & Fun - Jonathan Graehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/categories/psychology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-04T04:13:15-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://graehl.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Graehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[graehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[quitting time]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/quitting-time/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-18T12:14:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/quitting-time</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>A meditation on despair: </div>


<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<p style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); margin-bottom: 0.2in;"> Say you yell every day at an/your eight year old girl for sloppy homework, admittedly a terrible thing to do but not uncommon, and eventually she thinks, "I'm terrible at everything" and gives up, so the standard interpretation of this is that she has lost self-confidence, she's been demoralized, and case by case you may be right, but there's another possibility which you should consider: she chooses to focus on "I'm terrible at everything" <i>so that</i> she can give up.  "If I agree to hate myself I only need a 60?  I'll be done in 10 minutes. " </p>
<p></p> It is precisely at this instant that a parent fails or succeeds, i.e. fails: do they teach the kid to prefer (find reinforcement in) the drudgery of boring, difficult work with little daily evidence of improvement, or do they teach the kid to prefer (find reinforcement in) about 20 minutes of sobbing hysterically and then off to Facebook and a sandwich?  Each human being is only able to learn to prefer one of those at a time.  Which one does the parent incentivize?<p></p> If you read this as laziness you have utterly missed the point. It's not laziness, because you're still working hard, but you are working purposelessly on purpose. The goal of your work is to be done the work, not to be better at work.<p></p> For a great many people this leads to an unconscious, default hierarchy in the mind, I'm not an epidemiologist but you got it in you sometime between the ages of 5 and 10: <br><p style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); margin-bottom: 0.2in;"> <br></p>
<p align="center" style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); margin-bottom: 0.2in;"><doing awesome> <br></doing></p>
<p align="center" style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); margin-bottom: 0.2in;"> is better than <br></p>
<p align="center" style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); margin-bottom: 0.2in;"><feeling terrible about yourself> <br></feeling></p> <p align="center" style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); margin-bottom: 0.2in;">is better than <br></p>
<p align="center" style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); margin-bottom: 0.2in;"> <the mental work of change></the></p>
<p style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); margin-bottom: 0.2in;"><br></p>
<p style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); margin-bottom: 0.2in;"> You should memorize this, it is running your life.  "I'm constantly thinking about ways to improve myself."  No, you're gunning the engine while you're up on blocks.  Obsessing and ruminating is a skill at which we are all tremendously accomplished, and admittedly that feels like mental work because it's exhausting and unrewarding, but you can no more ruminate your way through a life crisis than a differential equation.  So the parents unknowingly teach you to opt for <b>, and after a few years of childhood insecurity, you'll choose the Blue Pill begin the dreaming: someday and someplace you'll show someone how great you somehow are.  And after a few months with that someone they will eventually turn to you, look deep into your eyes, and say, "look, I don't have a swimming pool, but if I did I'd drown myself in it.  Holy Christ are you toxic."</b></p>
<p></p> "Well, my parents were really strict, they made me--" </blockquote>


<div>
<a href="http://thelastpsychiatrist.com/2012/06/amy_schumer_offers_you_a_look.html">via</a> </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lithium helps you get up in the morning]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/lithium-helps-you-get-up-in-the-morning/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-26T12:47:53-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/lithium-helps-you-get-up-in-the-morning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.readability.com/read?url=http%3A//www.psmag.com/health/researchers-crack-codes-for-lithium-electroshock-42273/">This article</a> claims as advance in the understanding of why <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithium_pharmacology">lithium helps protect the brain</a>. It turns out that it&rsquo;s at least partially due to forcing sleep. Insufficient sleep is extremely harmful:<p></p></p>

<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<p style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Droid Serif,Droid Sans,sans-serif; font-size: 16px; line-height: 22px; margin: 0px; padding: 0px 0px 15px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> by blocking the enzyme known as glycogen synthase kinase, or GSK3, lithium boosts the master clock’s strength threefold.</p>
<p style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Droid Serif,Droid Sans,sans-serif; font-size: 16px; line-height: 22px; margin: 0px; padding: 0px 0px 15px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> Understanding this mechanism, Meng says, companies are already developing drugs that can block GSK3, but which would be unlikely to trigger lithium’s unwelcome effects such as nausea, dry mouth, tremor, weakness and weight gain.</p> </blockquote>


<p></p>


<div>Now that a mechanism is known, perhaps new patentable synthetics that target just that mechanism, but with slightly different side effects, can provide a $billions cash cow. Lithium was probably underprescribed by the medical industry due to lack of financial incentive.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>I'd started low dose (1mg/day) lithium on the basis of a <a href="http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:YNH35x005wAJ:www.medicineispersonal.com/contest/1st+&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=us">literature review by Scott Siskind</a> on <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/a60/quantified_health_prize_results_announced/">LessWrong</a> and couldn't tell if it was only another nice multivitamin-like placebo, but I may have been sleeping and waking slightly better. Side effects were completely nonexistent for me at 1mg/day. An ordinary diet already supplies .5-3mg/day, though:</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;"><span style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; line-height: 19px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(247,247,248);">In 1985, the EPA, estimated that the daily lithium consumption for a 154 lb. adult ranges from 650 to 3,100 micrograms</span></blockquote>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>Lithium definitely decreases suicides. That's something. There are other claims of decent strength: <a href="http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2010/07/lithium-and-inflammation.html">http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2010/07/lithium-and-inflammation.html</a> and <a href="http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2011/02/lithium-and-longevity.html">http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2011/02/lithium-and-longevity.html</a>.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>It's suspicious to me when a medicine does so many seemingly different good things. But since the mechanism at least involves sleep, which is central, it's plausible. Also, there are other medicines (aspirin) that really do have several good effects (I assume because excess inflammation can be harmful in many different ways). It's suspicious to me when something has many good effects (speeds/slows several different natural chemical reactions) and no bad effects. I'd expect most tweaks to be only situationally good, or else it's just an accident that evolution hasn't stumbled upon and widely disseminated the capability to produce something analogous to the drug.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[brushes with celebrity]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/brushes-with-celebrity/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-07T12:31:16-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/brushes-with-celebrity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.overcomingbias.com/2012/05/illusory-power-transference.html">Robin Hanson describes research</a> about how a quick glad-handing by a CEO-figure makes people act boldly &ndash; with more presumed status:<p></p></p>

<div>
<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;"><span style="color: rgb(53,53,55); font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: 15px; line-height: 22px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">“Illusory Power Transference” is the academic name for feeling powerful due to a superficial connection to a powerful person, such as having once been in the same room</span></blockquote> <div>...</div>
<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<span style="background-color: rgb(255,255,255); color: rgb(53,53,55); font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: 15px; line-height: 22px;">Otherwise puzzling behavior can be explained by strong evolved desires to affiliate with high status (i.e., impressive or powerful) people. Apparently even very weak affiliations can make big differences. This can help explain our preferring live art and sport events, and our uncritical relations to academics, real estate agents, investment advisors, doctors, lawyers, etc.</span> </blockquote> <p></p>
<div>People often act as though everyone knows about every social interaction they have:</div>
<p></p>
<div>1. after recycling, or being told to buy a 'green' product, people feel sufficiently virtuous that they'll more likely turn down a panhandler later, effectively believing that their virtuous acts are generally known.</div> <p></p>
<div>2. after being turned down by one woman, a man will feel less confident approaching the next, even in a different venue.</div>
<p></p>
<div>In a small tribe, it would make sense to expect every interaction to eventually count (via reputation) with everyone. But celebrity is asymmetric. It's a millions to one (or for a CEO, thousands to one) relationship. There's little chance that the politician's handshake and warm words can be relied upon for anything.</div> <p></p>
<div>I think that the confidence (or lack of it) that carries over between independent encounters (without any small-town-gossip connection) still has power. When someone acts as though they'll be respected, they more often are. Most people can't fake this expectation. So, in a way, the information that George got a smile from the CEO does spread, dilutely.</div> </div>


<p></p>


<div>If you're rational about it, you'll make sure your high-status affiliations are actually known. Good luck not sounding like a self-promoting name-dropper, though - and there's nothing we despise more than obvious over-reaching status-gamers.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[give people(liars) time to reflect before answering, and isolate them from excuses.]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/give-peopleliars-time-to-reflect-before-answe/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-07T12:41:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/give-peopleliars-time-to-reflect-before-answe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>
<a href="http://home.medewerker.uva.nl/s.shalvi/bestanden/Shalvi%20et%20al_Honesty%20requires%20time_PS.pdf">Honesty requires time (and lack of justifications) [Shalvi et al]</a>:</div>


<p></p>


<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: #cccccc; border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;"><span style="color: #333333; font-family: Verdana,Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; line-height: 20px; background-color: #ffffff;">the average roll, if people reported honestly, should have been 3.5. This gave them a baseline from which to calculate participants’ honesty. Those forced to enter their results within 20 seconds, the researchers found, reported a mean roll of 4.6. Those who were not under any time pressure reported a mean roll of 3.9. </span></blockquote>


<p></p>


<div>This in an experiment with a reward of about $10 for lying.</div>


<p></p>


<div>My guess: immediate temptation to cheat for $10 if you think you can get away with it. On reflection, caution accelerates:</div>


<p></p>


<div>1. The gain is small.</div>


<div>2. Maybe people will find out via mechanism X I didn't think of (hidden cameras?)</div>


<div>3. maybe my report of 6 will be suspicious. maybe a 5 ... no, may as well just go with my original 3 ...</div>


<div>4. How will I feel having cheated? How good will I feel going away having a story of how I was honest even when it cost me?</div>


<div>5. I want to impress my psych teacher with how honest we college freshmen are.</div>


<div>6. Now that I've hesitated so long, I feel even more cautious. I've spent so much time deliberating, when I could have just taken the extra $5 immediately ... I must actually not want to cheat.</div>


<p></p>


<div>Perhaps also noteworthy: the above experiment was with 3 dice rolls, but the instruction to report the first. In a second experiment with only 1 die roll, the averages result claimed by both the hurry-up and take-your-time groups was 0.2-0.4 lower. This suggest that people in the 3 die roll group felt more comfortable cheating by reporting the 2nd or 3rd roll, perhaps in their mind lamely equating it with what could have been the 1st roll, or having a justification ready of having honestly misunderstood (I doubt anyone did honestly misunderstand). A difference of 0.2 is surely significant (comparing between N=76 and N=74 freshmen under the 3-dice and 1-die conditions).</div>


<p></p>


<div>
<a href="http://www.economist.com/node/21551447">via</a> (a not very useful Economist article, if you've read this far).</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[habits]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/habits/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-29T16:25:48-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/habits</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin-top: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<blockquote style="border-left-width: 2px; border-left-style: solid; border-left-color: rgb(51,102,153); padding-left: 4px; margin-top: 5px; margin-bottom: 5px; margin-left: 5px; margin-right: 15px; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; line-height: 16px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> <p style="margin-top: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 0px;">The process within our brains that creates habits is a three-step loop. First, there is a cue, a trigger that tells your brain to go into automatic mode and which habit to use. Then there is the routine, which can be physical or mental or emotional. Finally, there is a reward, which helps your brain ﬁgure out if this particular loop is worth remembering for the future. Over time, this loop — cue, routine, reward; cue, routine, reward — becomes more and more automatic. The cue and reward become neurologically intertwined until a sense of craving emerges. What’s unique about cues and rewards, however, is how subtle they can be. Neurological studies like the ones in Graybiel’s lab have revealed that some cues span just milliseconds. And rewards can range from the obvious (like the sugar rush that a morning doughnut habit provides) to the infinitesimal (like the barely noticeable — but measurable — sense of relief the brain experiences after successfully navigating the driveway). Most cues and rewards, in fact, happen so quickly and are so slight that we are hardly aware of them at all. But our neural systems notice and use them to build automatic behaviors.</p>
<p></p> Habits aren’t destiny — they can be ignored, changed or replaced. But it’s also true that once the loop is established and a habit emerges, your brain stops fully participating in decision-making. So unless you deliberately ﬁght a habit — unless you ﬁnd new cues and rewards — the old pattern will unfold automatically. [...] </blockquote>
<blockquote style="border-left-width: 2px; border-left-style: solid; border-left-color: rgb(51,102,153); padding-left: 4px; margin-top: 5px; margin-bottom: 5px; margin-left: 5px; margin-right: 15px; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; line-height: 16px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> <p style="margin-top: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 0px;">Luckily, simply understanding how habits work makes them easier to control. Take, for instance, a series of studies conducted a few years ago at Columbia University and the University of Alberta. Researchers wanted to understand how exercise habits emerge. In one project, 256 members of a health-insurance plan were invited to classes stressing the importance of exercise. Half the participants received an extra lesson on the theories of habit formation (the structure of the habit loop) and were asked to identify cues and rewards that might help them develop exercise routines.</p>
<p></p> The results were dramatic. Over the next four months, those participants who deliberately identified cues and rewards spent twice as much time exercising as their peers. Other studies have yielded similar results. According to another recent paper, if you want to start running in the morning, it’s essential that you choose a simple cue (like always putting on your sneakers before breakfast or leaving your running clothes next to your bed) and a clear reward (like a midday treat or even the sense of accomplishment that comes from ritually recording your miles in a log book). After a while, your brain will start anticipating that reward — craving the treat or the feeling of accomplishment — and there will be a measurable neurological impulse to lace up your jogging shoes each morning.<p></p> Our relationship to e-mail operates on the same principle. When a computer chimes or a smartphone vibrates with a new message, the brain starts anticipating the neurological “pleasure” (even if we don’t recognize it as such) that clicking on the e-mail and reading it provides. That expectation, if unsatisfied, can build until you find yourself moved to distraction by the thought of an e-mail sitting there unread — even if you know, rationally, it’s most likely not important. On the other hand, once you remove the cue by disabling the buzzing of your phone or the chiming of your computer, the craving is never triggered, and you’ll find, over time, that you’re able to work productively for long stretches without checking your in-box. [...] </blockquote>
<blockquote style="border-left-width: 2px; border-left-style: solid; border-left-color: rgb(51,102,153); padding-left: 4px; margin-top: 5px; margin-bottom: 5px; margin-left: 5px; margin-right: 15px; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; line-height: 16px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> <p style="margin-top: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 0px;">When they got back to P.&amp; G.’s headquarters, the researchers watched their videotapes again. Now they knew what to look for and saw their mistake in scene after scene. Cleaning has its own habit loops that already exist. In one video, when a woman walked into a dirty room (cue), she started sweeping and picking up toys (routine), then she examined the room and smiled when she was done (reward). In another, a woman scowled at her unmade bed (cue), proceeded to straighten the blankets and comforter (routine) and then sighed as she ran her hands over the freshly plumped pillows (reward). P.&amp; G. had been trying to create a whole new habit with Febreze, but what they really needed to do was piggyback on habit loops that were already in place. The marketers needed to position Febreze as something that came at the end of the cleaning ritual, the reward, rather than as a whole new cleaning routine.</p>
<p></p> The company printed new ads showing open windows and gusts of fresh air. More perfume was added to the Febreze formula, so that instead of merely neutralizing odors, the spray had its own distinct scent. Television commercials were filmed of women, having finished their cleaning routine, using Febreze to spritz freshly made beds and just-laundered clothing. Each ad was designed to appeal to the habit loop: when you see a freshly cleaned room (cue), pull out Febreze (routine) and enjoy a smell that says you’ve done a great job (reward). When you finish making a bed (cue), spritz Febreze (routine) and breathe a sweet, contented sigh (reward). Febreze, the ads implied, was a pleasant treat, not a reminder that your home stinks. <p></p> And so Febreze, a product originally conceived as a revolutionary way to destroy odors, became an air freshener used once things are already clean. The Febreze revamp occurred in the summer of 1998. Within two months, sales doubled. A year later, the product brought in $230 million. Since then Febreze has spawned dozens of spinoffs — air fresheners, candles and laundry detergents — that now account for sales of more than $1 billion a year. Eventually, P.&amp; G. began mentioning to customers that, in addition to smelling sweet, Febreze can actually kill bad odors. Today it’s one of the top-selling products in the world. [...] </blockquote>
<blockquote style="border-left-width: 2px; border-left-style: solid; border-left-color: rgb(51,102,153); padding-left: 4px; margin-top: 5px; margin-bottom: 5px; margin-left: 5px; margin-right: 15px; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; line-height: 16px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> <p style="margin-top: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 0px;">But when some customers were going through a major life event, like graduating from college or getting a new job or moving to a new town, their shopping habits became flexible in ways that were both predictable and potential gold mines for retailers. The study found that when someone marries, he or she is more likely to start buying a new type of coffee. When a couple move into a new house, they’re more apt to purchase a different kind of cereal. When they divorce, there’s an increased chance they’ll start buying different brands of beer.</p>
<p></p> Consumers going through major life events often don’t notice, or care, that their shopping habits have shifted, but retailers notice, and they care quite a bit. At those unique moments, Andreasen wrote, customers are “vulnerable to intervention by marketers.” In other words, a precisely timed advertisement, sent to a recent divorcee or new homebuyer, can change someone’s shopping patterns for years. [...] </blockquote>
<blockquote style="border-left-width: 2px; border-left-style: solid; border-left-color: rgb(51,102,153); padding-left: 4px; margin-top: 5px; margin-bottom: 5px; margin-left: 5px; margin-right: 15px; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; line-height: 16px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> <p style="margin-top: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: 0px;">Before I met Andrew Pole, before I even decided to write a book about the science of habit formation, I had another goal: I wanted to lose weight.</p>
<p></p> I had got into a bad habit of going to the cafeteria every afternoon and eating a chocolate-chip cookie, which contributed to my gaining a few pounds. Eight, to be precise. I put a Post-it note on my computer reading “NO MORE COOKIES.” But every afternoon, I managed to ignore that note, wander to the cafeteria, buy a cookie and eat it while chatting with colleagues. Tomorrow, I always promised myself, I’ll muster the willpower to resist.<p></p> Tomorrow, I ate another cookie.<p></p>When I started interviewing experts in habit formation, I concluded each interview by asking what I should do. The first step, they said, was to figure out my habit loop. The routine was simple: every afternoon, I walked to the cafeteria, bought a cookie and ate it while chatting with friends.<p></p> Next came some less obvious questions: What was the cue? Hunger? Boredom? Low blood sugar? And what was the reward? The taste of the cookie itself? The temporary distraction from my work? The chance to socialize with colleagues?<p></p> Rewards are powerful because they satisfy cravings, but we’re often not conscious of the urges driving our habits in the first place. So one day, when I felt a cookie impulse, I went outside and took a walk instead. The next day, I went to the cafeteria and bought a coffee. The next, I bought an apple and ate it while chatting with friends. You get the idea. I wanted to test different theories regarding what reward I was really craving. Was it hunger? (In which case the apple should have worked.) Was it the desire for a quick burst of energy? (If so, the coffee should suffice.) Or, as turned out to be the answer, was it that after several hours spent focused on work, I wanted to socialize, to make sure I was up to speed on office gossip, and the cookie was just a convenient excuse? When I walked to a colleague’s desk and chatted for a few minutes, it turned out, my cookie urge was gone.<p></p> All that was left was identifying the cue.<p></p>Deciphering cues is hard, however. Our lives often contain too much information to figure out what is triggering a particular behavior. Do you eat breakfast at a certain time because you’re hungry? Or because the morning news is on? Or because your kids have started eating? Experiments have shown that most cues fit into one of five categories: location, time, emotional state, other people or the immediately preceding action. So to figure out the cue for my cookie habit, I wrote down five things the moment the urge hit:<p></p> Where are you? (Sitting at my desk.)<p></p>What time is it? (3:36 p.m.)<p></p>What’s your emotional state? (Bored.)<p></p>Who else is around? (No one.)<p></p>What action preceded the urge? (Answered an e-mail.)<p></p> The next day I did the same thing. And the next. Pretty soon, the cue was clear: I always felt an urge to snack around 3:30.<p></p>Once I figured out all the parts of the loop, it seemed fairly easy to change my habit. But the psychologists and neuroscientists warned me that, for my new behavior to stick, I needed to abide by the same principle that guided Procter &amp; Gamble in selling Febreze: To shift the routine — to socialize, rather than eat a cookie — I needed to piggyback on an existing habit. So now, every day around 3:30, I stand up, look around the newsroom for someone to talk to, spend 10 minutes gossiping, then go back to my desk. The cue and reward have stayed the same. Only the routine has shifted. It doesn’t feel like a decision, any more than the M.I.T. rats made a decision to run through the maze. It’s now a habit. I’ve lost 21 pounds since then (12 of them from changing my cookie ritual). </blockquote>
</blockquote>


<div> summary <a href="http://lesswrong.com/r/discussion/lw/a8u/link_how_habits_control_our_behavior_and_how_to/">via</a> - from an <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/02/19/magazine/shopping-habits.html">article</a> with linkbait headline I'd avoided reading.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
