<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sex | Science & Fun - Jonathan Graehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/tag/sex/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-24T10:56:51-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://graehl.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Graehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[graehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[girl ... you lookin' so fine tonight, it must be 10 days before your menses]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2011/07/06/girl-you-lookin-so-fine-tonight-it-must-be-10/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-06T21:22:46-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2011/07/06/girl-you-lookin-so-fine-tonight-it-must-be-10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<pre><code>  More &lt;a href="http://graehl.org/tagIncognito"&gt;Incognito&lt;/a&gt;, on our instinctual assessment of sexual attractiveness:&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Women at peak fertility (~10 days prior to their period) are judged more beautiful - proved by stripper income as well as lab results.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Briefly glimpsed people excite us as though the uncertainty will all pan out in the direction of more beauty (encouraging further investigation) - this also works for briefly flashed photos.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Pale skin shows imperfections better, so allows for better judgment of health (if so, then the above "glimpse" effect would make darker skinned people initially seem more exciting). I always believed this preference to be learned, not innate.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Women with a .67-.8 waist:hip ratio are most exciting to men (given a fixed overall slenderness).&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Dissimilar genes ("MHC" - "histocompatability") are identified by scent (by their chemical effects and not directly, I presume) in mice, and lead to sexual preference (presumably because dissimilarity in those genes is important to avoid inbreeding-type recessive defects). Similar receptors exist in humans, and sweaty t-shirts are preferred with increasingly dissimilar MHC.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Women prefer the sweaty t-shirts of more physically masculine men when fertile; otherwise they don't care as much or can't detect it as well.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Women tolerate feminine-looking men (e.g. soft, youthful face) relatively more when they're less fertile.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Women's menstrual cycles may change after smelling another woman's sweat.&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Activating vasopressin receptors in the brain causes pair-bonding;polygamous species can be made monogamous and vice versa by manipulating the receptors for vasopressin, or its prevalence. For human males, there's already a genetic test (in the area known to code for vasopressin receptors) that predicts infidelity and partners' dissatisfaction (did they measure vasopressin response directly?)&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  Foxes pair-bond for a single breeding season (the male stays long enough to help raise the kits).
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
