<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: science | Science & Fun - Jonathan Graehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/tag/science/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-25T13:04:44-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://graehl.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Graehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[graehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Delusional Self-Esteem vs. Social Isolation]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2013/06/11/delusional-self-esteem-vs-social-isolation/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-11T23:06:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2013/06/11/delusional-self-esteem-vs-social-isolation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>People who feel isolated seek out existing allies and increase their criticism of non-allies (hello, Internet!). Apparently these routines (and so probably the feeling of isolation) can be suppressed by imagining yourself invulnerable to physical injury. Previous studies have shown that ibuprofen reduces the pain of social rejection.</p>

<p>
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/thatdjspider/3889784136/" title="Wolverine and Rachel Summers, DragonCon 2009 / Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3618/3889784136_15c1753d1c.jpg" width="373" height="500" alt="Wolverine and Rachel Summers, DragonCon 2009"></a>
</p>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>Simulating physical invulnerability lessened exclusion-triggered negative attitudes toward stigmatized groups, and<br/>simulating physical invulnerability lessened the desire for social connection.</p></p><p><p>[They fantasized] “It will be an amazing ability, but you must keep it absolutely secret. If you purposely tell anyone or show off your power, you will lose it forever.’”</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>Seriously</strong> <cite>Science? <a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/seriouslyscience/?p=305">http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/seriouslyscience/?p=305</a> Pretending to Have Superpowers</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Compared to people who imagined gaining the ability to fly (secretly), people who imagined (secret) physical invulnerability executed less of the anti-isolation routines like putting down outsiders or socializing positively with allies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Aquatic Apes Became Humans?]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2013/06/05/aquatic-apes-became-humans/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-05T19:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2013/06/05/aquatic-apes-became-humans</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Maybe humans evolved not from tree-apes, but diving-underwater
apes. We have thick skulls not just to protect our huge brains, but as
ballast to allow us to dive. Fish oil and iodine are good for a
developing brain because it was plentiful in our evolutionary
environment.</p>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><ol><br/><li><p>An extensive overview of the literature by Stephen Munro showed that virtually all known archaic Homo [= pre-Homo sapien] sites (including those in ‘savanna’) were associated with permanent water and edible shellfish.</p></li><br/><li><p>Only regular diving can explain archaic Homo’s pachy-osteo-sclerosis (POS), the extreme thickness and density of cranial and postcranial bones of most erectus-like fossils&hellip; . POS is only seen in slow littoral divers, e.g. dugong and manatee, walrus, Kolponomos, pakicetids, Odobenocetops, and Thalassocnus spp. Marine biologists agree POS has a hydrostatic function (ballast).</p></li><br/><li><p>The abundant brain-specific nutrients in aquatic foods (e.g. DHA, iodine) facilitated fast brain growth (sapiens’ poorer post-aquatic diet required a longer youth to grow the same brain size).</p></li><br/><li><p>Man is the opposite of a savanna inhabitant. Humans lack sun-reflecting fur, but have thermo-insulative subcutaneous fat layers, which are never seen in savanna mammals. We have a water- and sodium-wasting cooling system of abundant sweat glands, totally unfit for a dry environment. Our maximal urine concentration is much too low for a savanna-dwelling mammal. We need much more water than other primates, and have to drink more often than savanna inhabitants, yet we cannot drink large quantities at a time.</p></li><br/><li><p>Maps of human population densities show that, although we have become fully terrestrial today, we are still a waterside species, and almost half of human dietary calories still come from the water (e.g. rice, aquaculture, fish, shell- and crayfish).</p></li><br/></ol></p><p><br/><p></p><footer><strong>Seth Roberts <a href="http://blog.sethroberts.net/2013/06/04/aquatic-ape-theory-revised/">http://blog.sethroberts.net/2013/06/04/aquatic-ape-theory-revised/</a> summary of Marc Verhaegen&rsquo;s theory</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><a href="http://scienceblogs.com/gregladen/2013/01/30/common-misconceptions-and-unproven-assumptions-about-the-aquatic-ape-theory/">Marc Verhaegen&rsquo;s original article</a> &ndash; obviously this is only speculation.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[explaining rat red-wine superpowers]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2013/03/18/explaining-rat-red-wine-superpowers/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-18T17:32:11-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2013/03/18/explaining-rat-red-wine-superpowers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>Resveratrol, found in small amounts in red wine, is well-known to protect mice from aging and obesity. It's not yet known whether it works in humans (it's expensive enough that you wouldn't want to just take a bunch of it on speculation). There are some synthetic resveratrol analogues already developed in research, but again, they're not cheaply available (nor assuredly free of side effects).</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>A fantastic series of experiments isolates the mechanism for the (in rats) benefits of the resveratrol-like family, confirming suspicions that it functions by activating a protein involved in energy metabolism, SIRT1*</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>1. answer an objection (that an artificial fluourescent marker used in test tube studies linking resveratrol turned out to be necessary for the reaction to occur) by locating the third ingredient existing in the rat cells (tryptophan, a common amino acid, turned out to suffice).</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>2. generate modified versions of SIRT1 by playing with mouse genes (because synthesizing organic chemicals is tricky; if you just want randomly different versions, you can do this by fuzzing genes of organisms that produce it**). It's expensive to analyze a complicated molecule, so they just looked at the gene versions (out of 2000 they generated) that had no benefit from resveratrol, and found some minimal change to the structure of regular SIRT1 that disables the effect. This is almost certainly where resveratrol acts on SIRT1.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>3. Using one of their 2000 mutant lines that blocked the resveratrol effect, they tried all the resveratrol-analogues, and found that none of them worked. This adds a little confidence that the analogues all work by the same mechanism.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>4. finally, they verify the results in (mouse) skin and muscle cells by replacing the normal SIRT1 gene w/ their mutant variant, and showing that this blocked the resveratrol benefit (they should have done a "placebo" version of this where they replace it with the normal version). I wonder why they can't do this for human cells? We mostly care if this can benefit humans.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>I wonder if enhancing SIRT1 will turn out to have harms as well as benefits. If not, then it can only be because producing resveratrol wasn't conveniently available as a mutation in mammals. We could also ask why we don't produce more SIRT1, even if we don't have a multiplier available to enhance its effectiveness. I'd guess that producing SIRT1 is expensive.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>
<div>*  It's interesting that resveratrol enhances SIRT1 activity, because it's harder to find a chemical that speeds up a protein's good functions than it is to find one that interferes (usually by binding to the useful location to deny it to other parties).</div> </div>


<p></p>


<div>** although you don't necessarily build a full organism; it looks like they fuzzed the genes but did the reactions in a test tube?<br>
</div>


<p></p>


<p><a href="http://hms.harvard.edu/news/new-study-validates-longevity-pathway-3-7-13">via</a> (Science, so it&rsquo;s peer reviewed)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[omega-6 (vegetable oil) harmful (N=500, P=.05, large effect)]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2013/03/15/omega-6-vegetable-oil-harmful-n500-p05-large/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-15T06:13:58-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2013/03/15/omega-6-vegetable-oil-harmful-n500-p05-large</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the main claims of &ldquo;paleo&rdquo; bloggers is that it&rsquo;s better to have saturated fat than polyunsaturated vegetable oils (except flaxseed oil), that omega-3 is good polyunsaturated and omega-6 is bad past some ratio of 6:3.<p></p></p>

<div>Experts endorsed by the US gov, Harvard, and in general the high-status pro diet/medicine institution got this badly wrong, <a href="http://blog.sethroberts.net/2013/03/15/omega-6-is-bad-for-you/">Seth Roberts notes</a> that there's some strong new evidence (<a href="http://www.bmj.com/content/346/bmj.e8707">reanalysis of existing randomized/controlled N=500 data</a>):<br> </div>


<p></p>


<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<p style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Trebuchet MS,Lucida Grande,Verdana,Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 18.71875px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(153,204,153);"> As these studies go, it was relatively small, only about 500 subjects. The main results:</p>
<blockquote style="color: rgb(119,119,119); margin: 15px 30px 0px 10px; padding-left: 20px; border-left-width: 5px; border-left-style: solid; border-left-color: rgb(221,221,221); font-family: Trebuchet MS,Lucida Grande,Verdana,Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 18.71875px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(153,204,153);"> <p>Compared with the control group, <strong>the intervention group had an increased risk of all cause mortality (17.6% v 11.8%</strong>[emphasis added]; hazard ratio 1.62 (95% confidence interval 1.00 to 2.64); P=0.051), cardiovascular mortality (17.2% v 11.0%; 1.70 (1.03 to 2.80); P=0.037), and mortality from coronary heart disease (16.3% v 10.1%; 1.74 (1.04 to 2.92); P=0.036).</p> </blockquote>
<p style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Trebuchet MS,Lucida Grande,Verdana,Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 18.71875px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(153,204,153);">A 50% increase in death rate! The safflower oil was so damaging that even this small study yielded significant differences.</p> <p style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Trebuchet MS,Lucida Grande,Verdana,Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 18.71875px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(153,204,153);">The authors go on to show that this result (omega-6 is bad for you) is supported by other studies. Walter Willett and countless other experts were quite wrong on the biggest health issue of our time (how to reduce heart disease, the #1 cause of death).</p> </blockquote>


<div>I'm still prepared to accept that, for whatever reason, red meat intake is correlated with (even causes) a large increase in mortality (heart disease and colon cancer if I recall correctly). But is the saturated fat the culprit? And the type of diet fed to beef makes a difference in the lipids we consume (feed them with omega 6 or trans fats and it would be understandably unhealthy to eat). But pros were wrong about cholesterol (lowering it with statins is harmful) and vegetable oil.</div>


<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[bone broth has (some) lead]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2013/02/27/bone-broth-has-some-lead/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-27T17:52:37-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2013/02/27/bone-broth-has-some-lead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<span style="">bones are known to sequester the heavy metal lead, contamination with which is widespread throughout the modern environment. Such sequestered lead can then be mobilised from the bones ... </span><span style=""> </span><span style="">broth made from skin and cartilage [of already cooked chicken] </span><span style="">and chicken-bone broth, were both found to have markedly high lead concentrations, of 9.5 and 7.01 μg L</span><sup style="">−1</sup><br> </blockquote>


<p></p>


<p><a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0306987713000133">via</a><p></p></p>

<div>Caveat: this is only 10x the amount in their tap water. I'm not sure if this is enough to matter, but small amounts of lead hurt IQ detectably (on a population level)</div>


<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
