<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: science | Science & Fun - Jonathan Graehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/categories/science/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-04T04:13:15-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://graehl.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Graehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[graehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lithium helps you get up in the morning]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/lithium-helps-you-get-up-in-the-morning/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-26T12:47:53-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/lithium-helps-you-get-up-in-the-morning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.readability.com/read?url=http%3A//www.psmag.com/health/researchers-crack-codes-for-lithium-electroshock-42273/">This article</a> claims as advance in the understanding of why <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithium_pharmacology">lithium helps protect the brain</a>. It turns out that it&rsquo;s at least partially due to forcing sleep. Insufficient sleep is extremely harmful:<p></p></p>

<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<p style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Droid Serif,Droid Sans,sans-serif; font-size: 16px; line-height: 22px; margin: 0px; padding: 0px 0px 15px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> by blocking the enzyme known as glycogen synthase kinase, or GSK3, lithium boosts the master clock’s strength threefold.</p>
<p style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Droid Serif,Droid Sans,sans-serif; font-size: 16px; line-height: 22px; margin: 0px; padding: 0px 0px 15px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> Understanding this mechanism, Meng says, companies are already developing drugs that can block GSK3, but which would be unlikely to trigger lithium’s unwelcome effects such as nausea, dry mouth, tremor, weakness and weight gain.</p> </blockquote>


<p></p>


<div>Now that a mechanism is known, perhaps new patentable synthetics that target just that mechanism, but with slightly different side effects, can provide a $billions cash cow. Lithium was probably underprescribed by the medical industry due to lack of financial incentive.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>I'd started low dose (1mg/day) lithium on the basis of a <a href="http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:YNH35x005wAJ:www.medicineispersonal.com/contest/1st+&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=us">literature review by Scott Siskind</a> on <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/a60/quantified_health_prize_results_announced/">LessWrong</a> and couldn't tell if it was only another nice multivitamin-like placebo, but I may have been sleeping and waking slightly better. Side effects were completely nonexistent for me at 1mg/day. An ordinary diet already supplies .5-3mg/day, though:</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;"><span style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; line-height: 19px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(247,247,248);">In 1985, the EPA, estimated that the daily lithium consumption for a 154 lb. adult ranges from 650 to 3,100 micrograms</span></blockquote>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>Lithium definitely decreases suicides. That's something. There are other claims of decent strength: <a href="http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2010/07/lithium-and-inflammation.html">http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2010/07/lithium-and-inflammation.html</a> and <a href="http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2011/02/lithium-and-longevity.html">http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2011/02/lithium-and-longevity.html</a>.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>It's suspicious to me when a medicine does so many seemingly different good things. But since the mechanism at least involves sleep, which is central, it's plausible. Also, there are other medicines (aspirin) that really do have several good effects (I assume because excess inflammation can be harmful in many different ways). It's suspicious to me when something has many good effects (speeds/slows several different natural chemical reactions) and no bad effects. I'd expect most tweaks to be only situationally good, or else it's just an accident that evolution hasn't stumbled upon and widely disseminated the capability to produce something analogous to the drug.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[red meat may be harmful]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/red-meat-may-be-harmful/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-09T21:29:48-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/red-meat-may-be-harmful</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>Red meat correlates with death.</div>


<p></p>


<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<span style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Trebuchet MS,Verdana,Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; line-height: 18px; text-align: left; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">The researchers carefully controlled</span><span style="color: rgb(51,51,51); line-height: 18px; text-align: left; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); font-family: verdana,arial,helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: x-small;"> <span style="font-size: small;"><span style="font-family: Times,Times New Roman,serif;">for intakes of total energy, whole grains, fruits, and vegetables; age; body mass index; race (white or nonwhite); smoking status</span><span style="font-family: Times,Times New Roman,serif;">; alcohol intake; physical activity level; multivitamin use; aspirin use; family history of diabetes mellitus, myocardial infarction, or cancer; and baseline history of diabetes mellitus, hypertension, or hypercholesterolemia. In women, they also adjusted the data for postmenopausal status and menopausal hormone use.</span></span></span>
</blockquote>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>Seems reasonably solid.</div>


<p></p>


<div>There are plenty of possible causal mechanisms, detailed <a href="http://donmatesz.blogspot.com/2012/04/harvard-meat-study.html">here</a>. Still no proof of overall causality, but it's enough evidence to encourage moderation.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>Things cooked at high heat (fried, well done, BBQed) are probably additionally unhealthy. </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[loss of brain matter with age (non-AD)]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/loss-of-brain-matter-with-age-non-ad/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-07T23:19:13-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/loss-of-brain-matter-with-age-non-ad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="p_embed p_image_embed">
<img alt="G10" src="http://graehl.org/images/2012/04/07/loss-of-brain-matter-with-age-non-ad/39852194-g10.jpg">
</div>


<p></p>


<div>Disgusting stuff. My poor brain!</div>


<div> </div>


<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">brain cell death (both neuronal and glial) is a process that begins at ~ 2 years of age – at least for the neurons that comprise the gray matter of the cerebral cortex, and which proceeds relentlessly throughout the individual’s lifetime (</span><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2896477/?tool=pubmed" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(17,85,204); font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">Giorgio, 2010</a><span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">) Brain cell loss and degeneration become morphologically apparent in the brain’s white matter by the time we are in our early 20’s, although there is evidence that more subtle changes have been afoot for much longer. (</span><a href="http://www.nmr.mgh.harvard.edu/~bradd/gabrieli_2004_nrn1323.pdf" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(17,85,204); font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">Hedden, 2004</a><span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">) Losses in gray matter volume proceed approximately</span><em style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> linearly</em><span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> with age in normal aging, and the average gray matter volume decreases from ~390 mL at age 22, to ~300 ml at age 82. (</span><a href="http://radiology.rsna.org/content/216/3/672.long" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(17,85,204); font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">Courchesne, 2000</a><span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">) Total loss in brain mass between age 20 and age 80 is, on average, ~450 g, or roughly 1/3</span><sup style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">rd</sup><span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> of our youthful brain volume.</span>
</blockquote>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div><a href="http://chronopause.com/index.php/2012/04/06/much-less-than-half-a-chance-part-5/">via</a></div>


<p></p>


<div>White matter peaks at 30 and declines slowly, though (note: the graphs are of different individuals at different ages; changes could also be due to generational environmental differences, perhaps).</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[give people(liars) time to reflect before answering, and isolate them from excuses.]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/give-peopleliars-time-to-reflect-before-answe/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-07T12:41:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/give-peopleliars-time-to-reflect-before-answe</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>
<a href="http://home.medewerker.uva.nl/s.shalvi/bestanden/Shalvi%20et%20al_Honesty%20requires%20time_PS.pdf">Honesty requires time (and lack of justifications) [Shalvi et al]</a>:</div>


<p></p>


<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: #cccccc; border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;"><span style="color: #333333; font-family: Verdana,Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; line-height: 20px; background-color: #ffffff;">the average roll, if people reported honestly, should have been 3.5. This gave them a baseline from which to calculate participants’ honesty. Those forced to enter their results within 20 seconds, the researchers found, reported a mean roll of 4.6. Those who were not under any time pressure reported a mean roll of 3.9. </span></blockquote>


<p></p>


<div>This in an experiment with a reward of about $10 for lying.</div>


<p></p>


<div>My guess: immediate temptation to cheat for $10 if you think you can get away with it. On reflection, caution accelerates:</div>


<p></p>


<div>1. The gain is small.</div>


<div>2. Maybe people will find out via mechanism X I didn't think of (hidden cameras?)</div>


<div>3. maybe my report of 6 will be suspicious. maybe a 5 ... no, may as well just go with my original 3 ...</div>


<div>4. How will I feel having cheated? How good will I feel going away having a story of how I was honest even when it cost me?</div>


<div>5. I want to impress my psych teacher with how honest we college freshmen are.</div>


<div>6. Now that I've hesitated so long, I feel even more cautious. I've spent so much time deliberating, when I could have just taken the extra $5 immediately ... I must actually not want to cheat.</div>


<p></p>


<div>Perhaps also noteworthy: the above experiment was with 3 dice rolls, but the instruction to report the first. In a second experiment with only 1 die roll, the averages result claimed by both the hurry-up and take-your-time groups was 0.2-0.4 lower. This suggest that people in the 3 die roll group felt more comfortable cheating by reporting the 2nd or 3rd roll, perhaps in their mind lamely equating it with what could have been the 1st roll, or having a justification ready of having honestly misunderstood (I doubt anyone did honestly misunderstand). A difference of 0.2 is surely significant (comparing between N=76 and N=74 freshmen under the 3-dice and 1-die conditions).</div>


<p></p>


<div>
<a href="http://www.economist.com/node/21551447">via</a> (a not very useful Economist article, if you've read this far).</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[memory is a series of hexagonal tubes]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/memory-is-a-series-of-hexagonal-tubes/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-13T10:46:28-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/memory-is-a-series-of-hexagonal-tubes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.readability.com/articles/ge1zprum">via</a> - <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microtubules">hexagonal tubes</a> are 15% of the brain&rsquo;s protein. Previously, we knew that long term potentiation of synapses features a hexagonal enzyme, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ca2%2B/calmodulin-dependent_protein_kinase">CaMKII</a>, which carries 6 bits of information (presence or absence of phosphorus at each of its 6 corners).<p></p></p>

<div>The new result is that computer models have shown that the same CaMKII that's involved in potentiating synapses, can also fit inside the hexagonal "microtubules" and write (or read; probably both - I'm not clear) the 6 phosphorylation bits in a slice of the microtubule. Probably microtubules, which are long, can hold very many 6-bit bytes.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>It's known that long term memories are lost if recalled and not stored. I could imagine the transfer of molecules from microtubules having this characteristic (if you don't put them back when you're done, they're gone).</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>CaMKII and microtubules exist in non-brain and non-human tissue as well.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
