<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: sociology | Science & Fun - Jonathan Graehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/tag/sociology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-25T13:04:44-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://graehl.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Graehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[graehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[nothing changes (people)]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2012/09/15/nothing-changes-people/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-15T18:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2012/09/15/nothing-changes-people</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: #cccccc; border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<p style="line-height: 21px; padding: 0px 6px 0px 0px; font-size: 14px; color: #272727; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; background-color: #ffffff;">a clever 1987 article by sociologist Peter H. Rossi, who distilled <a href="http://www.asanet.org/footnotes/dec06/indextwo.html" style="color: #035781; text-decoration: initial; font-weight: bold;">years of experience evaluating social programs</a> into a few simple “metallic laws”:</p>
<blockquote style="border-left-width: 5px; border-left-style: solid; border-left-color: #dddddd; line-height: 18px; margin-left: 20px; padding-left: 15px; background-color: #eeeeee; color: #272727; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: 12px;">
<p style="line-height: 21px; padding: 0px 6px 0px 0px; font-size: 14px;">A dramatic but slightly overdrawn view of two decades of evaluation efforts can be stated as a set of “laws,” each summarizing some strong tendency that can be discerned in that body of materials. Following a 19th Century practice that has fallen into disuse in social science, these laws are named after substances of varying durability, roughly indexing each law’s robustness.</p>
<p style="line-height: 21px; padding: 0px 6px 0px 0px; font-size: 14px;"><em>The Iron Law of Evaluation</em>: The expected value of any net impact assessment of any large scale social program is zero.<br>The Iron Law arises from the experience that few impact assessments of large scale social programs have found that the programs in question had any net impact. The law also means that, based on the evaluation efforts of the last twenty years, the best a priori estimate of the net impact assessment of any program is zero, i.e., that the program will have no effect.<br> <span> </span><br><em>The Stainless Steel Law of Evaluation</em>: The better designed the impact assessment of a social program, the more likely is the resulting estimate of net impact to be zero.<br>This law means that the more technically rigorous the net impact assessment, the more likely are its results to be zero—or no effect. Specifically, this law implies that estimating net impacts through randomized controlled experiments, the avowedly best approach to estimating net impacts, is more likely to show zero effects than other less rigorous approaches.</p>
<p style="line-height: 21px; padding: 0px 6px 0px 0px; font-size: 14px;"><em>The Brass Law of Evaluation</em>: The more social programs are designed to change individuals, the more likely the net impact of the program will be zero.<br> This law means that social programs designed to rehabilitate individuals by changing them in some way or another are more likely to fail. The Brass Law may appear to be redundant since all programs, including those designed to deal with individuals, are covered by the Iron Law. This redundancy is intended to emphasize the especially difficult task faced in designing and implementing effective programs that are designed to rehabilitate individuals.</p>
<p style="line-height: 21px; padding: 0px 6px 0px 0px; font-size: 14px;"><em>The Zinc Law of Evaluation</em>: Only those programs that are likely to fail are evaluated.<br>Of the several metallic laws of evaluation, the zinc law has the most optimistic slant since it implies that there are effective programs but that such effective programs are never evaluated. It also implies that if a social program is effective, that characteristic is obvious enough and hence policy makers and others who sponsor and fund evaluations decide against evaluation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="line-height: 21px; padding: 0px 6px 0px 0px; font-size: 14px; color: #272727; font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; background-color: #ffffff;">Sociology, of course, is not physics. It has no, well, ironclad truths. In fact, Rossi wrote that the Iron Law is “somewhat spongy and therefore easily, although not frequently, broken.” But the Stainless Steel law in particular accords with my own experience examining the literature on the impacts of microfinance (which is mostly about microcredit). The better done the study, the more muted the effects found. This is <a href="http://blogs.cgdev.org/open_book/2009/06/why-i-doubt-most-microfinance-impact-studies.php" style="color: #035781; text-decoration: initial; font-weight: bold;">why I doubt most microfinance impact studies</a>.</p>
</blockquote>


<p></p>


<p><a href="http://blogs.cgdev.org/open_book/2009/07/rossis-rules.php">via</a>, linked by <a href="http://www.gwern.net/">gwern</a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IQ matters. Education matters. (if money matters)]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2011/04/08/iq-matters-education-matters-if-money-matters/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-08T18:37:33-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2011/04/08/iq-matters-education-matters-if-money-matters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<pre><code>  Via Steve Sailer:&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;blockquote type="cite"&gt;&lt;div style="border-collapse: separate; color: rgb(0, 0, 0); font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 14px; font-style: normal; font-variant: normal; font-weight: normal; letter-spacing: normal; line-height: normal; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;
</code></pre>

<div style="border-collapse: collapse; font-size: 13px;"> <div style="margin: 0px; text-align: left;">Steve Hsu has a fascinating <a href="http://infoproc.blogspot.com/2011/04/earnings-effects-of-personality.html" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(34, 68, 187);">post </a>on a new paper by Nobel laureate economist/statistician James Heckman on the historic 1921 <a href="http://infoproc.blogspot.com/2009/11/do-advanced-education-and-challenging.html" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(34, 68, 187);">Terman Project</a> tracking more than 600 California white males with 135+ IQs over <a href="http://www.stanfordalumni.org/news/magazine/2000/julaug/articles/terman.html" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(34, 68, 187);">seven decades</a>.  You often hear about how this project shows that IQ doesn't matter because, say, none of Terman's Termites ever won the Nobel Prize.</div> <p></p> <div style="margin: 0px; text-align: left;">Heckman writes:</div> <blockquote> <div style="margin: 0px;">
<a href="http://infoproc.blogspot.com/2011/04/earnings-effects-of-personality.html" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(34, 68, 187);">The Effects of Education, Personality, and IQ on Earnings of High-Ability Men</a> </div> </blockquote> <blockquote> <div style="margin: 0px;">This paper estimates the internal rate of return (IRR) to education for men and women of the Terman sample, a 70-year long prospective cohort study of high-ability individuals. The Terman data is unique in that it not only provides full working-life earnings histories of the participants, but it also includes detailed profiles of each subject, including IQ and measures of latent personality traits. Having information on latent personality traits is significant as it allows us to measure the importance of personality on educational attainment and lifetime earnings.</div> </blockquote> <div style="margin: 0px; text-align: left;"> <div style="margin: 0px;">
<br> Heckman explains:</div> <blockquote class="posterous_short_quote">4.1 The Total Effect of Personality and IQ on Lifetime Earnings </blockquote> <blockquote class="posterous_medium_quote">We begin by analyzing how personality and IQ influence lifetime earnings. We use the sum of each individual's earnings from age 18 to age 75. ... With this simple regression, Conscientiousness and Extraversion are positively associated with earnings, while Agreeableness and Openness are negatively associated with earnings (although Openness fails to be statistically significant in this very simple exercise). Our measure of Neuroticism does not have a clear association with earnings. It is remarkable that even in this very high-IQ sample, where the range of observed IQs is clearly restricted, IQ still has a positive and statistically highly significant association with lifetime earnings.</blockquote> <p></p> <div style="margin: 0px;">This sounds about right from my long observations of highly successful entrepreneurs in a cognitively demanding field (market research): they were Intelligent (probably in the 125-160 range), Extraverted (good salesmen), Conscientious (i.e., hard-working), not too Neurotic (if they worried more about what could go wrong, they wouldn't start companies), and not too Agreeable (they could kick ass when necessary, and were very competitive -- raced yachts, drove imported Porsches that took six months to make street legal in the U.S.). They were probably more Open than average, although that has to do with them being entrepreneurs.</div> <p></p> <div style="margin: 0px;">Heckman goes on. </div> </div> <blockquote class="posterous_medium_quote">Finally, note that even when controlling for rich background variable [such as education], IQ maintains a statistically significant effect on lifetime earnings. Even though the effect is slightly diminished from the uncontrolled association of the first column, it is still sizeable. Malcolm Gladwell claims rather generally in his book "Outliers" that for the Terman men, IQ did not matter once family background and other observable personal characteristics were taken into account. While we do not want to argue that IQ has a larger role for the difference between 50 and 100, for example, than for the difference between 150 and 200, we do want to point out that even at the high end of the ability distribution, IQ has meaningful consequences.</blockquote> <p></p> <div style="margin: 0px; text-align: left;">In other words, people with 200 IQs will, on average, make more money than people with 150 IQs, all else being equal.<p></p>  For these very smart termites, getting more education increases lifetime income.</div> <blockquote class="posterous_medium_quote">One caveat about causality is in order... We partially follow this approach by using early measures of Openness and Extraversion. However, the other personality traits are measured at a time where the men are already in their working lives. Thus, these measures are more relevant to the observed earnings, but at the same time we cannot exclude the possibility that, for example, a high score on Neuroticism is a result of one's position in the workforce. </blockquote> <p></p> <div style="margin: 0px; text-align: left;">In other words, Terman asked personality questions back in 1922 of the youths that map well onto today's Big 5 personality traits of Openness and Extraversion, but the project didn't get around for a decade or two to asking questions that map to the other three Big personality components: Neuroticism, Agreeableness, and Conscientiousness. For example, my dad spent 40 years as a stress engineer at Lockheed worrying about whether the wings would snap off planes. Did he get into that career to start with because he always was a worry wart, or is he a worry wart today because he spent 40 years worrying about how to keep planes from crashing?</div> <p></p> <div style="margin: 0px; text-align: left;">You can read the whole study<span class="Apple-converted-space"> </span>
</div>
<a href="http://www.iza.org/conference_files/CoNoCoSk2011/gensowski_m6556.pdf" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(34, 68, 187);">here</a>.</div>


<p> </div></blockquote> I always thought that I&rsquo;d make more money by skipping grad school. But here I am doing academic research for not as much money as finance or silicon valley would provide &hellip; something is wrong. Either I love money, or I love academic research, or I&rsquo;m happily lazy.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
