<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: politics | Science & Fun - Jonathan Graehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/?tag=politics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-05T16:42:18-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://graehl.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Graehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[graehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Unstoppable Momentum of Social Activism]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2013/06/23/the-unstoppable-momentum-of-social-activism/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-23T00:12:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2013/06/23/the-unstoppable-momentum-of-social-activism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A do-good social cause just needs a spark of preliminary social-psych lab support to inspire unkillable cargo-cult group action. The desire to be one of the good guys who (know how to) save the world, coupled with confirmation bias and social proof, means unstoppable growth for even scientifically mistaken altruistic programs (failing to enact their values, or even causing regression).</p>

<p>Some examples of what we should probably (evidence suggests) NOT be doing: reducing violent entertainment or porn, telling everyone there&rsquo;s a rape culture in the U.S. which promotes rape, raising awareness that most people think black people are [insert negative racial stereotype here] and need to stop it IMMEDIATELY, telling workers that things they already do in fact constitute HARRASSMENT and are creating a HOSTILE WORKPLACE, making people identify with a group which is WRONG in any way (especially if obnoxious high-paid fly-by consultants are doing the telling). These are all, surprisingly, wrong.</p>

<p>Media coverage of clever new effects (priming!) begins as soon as the first small study wildly misinterprets N=10 lab experiments that may only last for 10 minutes, or, if the experimental script is varied slightly, might show an opposite effect. Please, let&rsquo;s not restructure everything in society without at <em>least</em> waiting for the replication studies.</p>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>Dahl and DellaVigna (2008), well aware of laboratory experiments that found violent media temporarily made subjects more violent, decided to investigate whether the opening weekends of blockbuster violent movies affected crime rates. Sure enough, they found they did</p></p><p><p>in the opposite of the expected direction. They found violent movies decreased crime 5% or more on their opening weekends, and that each violent movie that comes out probably prevents about 1000 assaults. Further, theres no displacement effect  the missing crimes dont pop back the following week, they simply never occur.</p></p><p><p>They hypothesize that every hour violent criminals are at the kind of movies that appeal to violent criminals is one hour more theyre not getting drunk or taking drugs or committing violent crimes. Although they dont mention it directly, other analyses have suggested that the movies have a sort of cathartic effect, satisfying their urge for violence without them having to commit it themselves.</p></p><p><p>An investigation into violent video games found essentially the same pattern: violent video games decrease crime while nonviolent video games have no effect.</p></p><p><p>In the US every 10% increase in Internet access causes a 7.3% decline in rape.</p></p><p><p>Sex criminals are less likely to consume pornography than the general population and start watching pornography at a later age.</p></p><p><p>We know exactly what happens when minorities are told tests are biased against them: they do worse on those tests. This is the essence of the idea of stereotype threat  for example, one can improve womens performance on a math test simply by telling them that the test is not biased against women.</p></p><p><p>DARE programs has found that they increase drug use, sometimes as much as 30%.</p></p><p><p>All studies on sensitivity training find that trainees express more awareness of sexual harassment than non-employees, but a study that went further and examined results found that trainees are less likely to perceive coercive sexual harassment, less willing to report sexual harassment, and more likely to blame the victim.</p></p><p><p>Foster &amp; Misra (2013) measured trivialization in both groups  that is, they asked them questions about how important faithfulness was to them. Consistent with their theory, the people who were told they were faithful said faithfulness was extremely important, but the people who were told they were unfaithful trivialized the behavior  who cares about fidelity anyway, infidelity is maybe a minor mistake but it doesnt really hurt anyone, people should really stop whining about infidelity all the time. To give you a feeling for the size of this effect, on a scale of one to seven, the faithful group rated the importance of being faithful at 5.4/7, and the unfaithful group rate the importance of being faithful at 2.9/7. In other words, by accusing them of being unfaithful, the experimenters had successfully gotten the participants to trivialize faithfulness.</p></p><p><p>The researchers theorized that this was the process called cognitive dissonance. Most people like themselves and want to continue to like themselves. If they are told that they, or their group, has a particular flaw, then instead of ceasing to like themselves it may be easier to just decide that flaw is not a big deal and they can have it while continuing to be the awesome people they secretly know they are.</p></p><p><p>Now not only do the experimental subjects here stop caring about being faithful, but everyone pushing a pro-fidelity line is a threat to their new identity. And the subjects werent even really unfaithful to begin with!</p></p><p><p>The most important factor in whether someone commits a crime is the likelihood she will be punished.  That suggests that if you discover that an abominable crime has (contrary to popular perception) a very low chance of punishment, it would be an excellent time to practice the virtue of silence.</p></p><p><p>Imagine I told you People from Comoros are not all homosexual! This is a damn lie, and anyone who says people from Comoros are homosexual is an insensitive jerk. Please join me in fighting the popular perception that everyone from Comoros is a flaming gay.</p><footer><strong>Alexander Scott <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2013/06/22/social-psychology-is-a-flamethrower/">http://slatestarcodex.com/2013/06/22/social-psychology-is-a-flamethrower/</a> Social Psychology is a Flamethrower</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>By reading the essay excerpted above (which I highly recommend in its entirety), I learned that there&rsquo;s about as much lab/epidemiological evidence (maybe more) for the opposite of what&rsquo;s usually prescribed by social-psych inspired progressive social engineering (raise awareness of rape culture / stereotype threat / culturally biased IQ/SAT tests, suppress violent entertainment and porn, etc.). It <em>does</em> suggest that the blanket denial of cognitive architecture between sexes might be a good thing as far as smoothing the way for women who want to science+math+engineer &ndash; one of the few progressive social projects that&rsquo;s working, or rather, would work, without all the &ldquo;we need to do more&rdquo; talk which is probably as damaging as Barbie&rsquo;s &ldquo;math is hard.&rdquo; Raising awareness of complicated/bad things can either backfire in the accused group, or due to loose recollection, raise awareness for the wrong idea (&ldquo;Obama is not a muslim&rdquo; becomes one year later &ldquo;I heard Obama is a muslim&rdquo;). And also that Comoros is full of flaming homosexual seagulls.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unconstitutional Pizza Delivery Dragnet / Failed AI Research Project]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2013/06/06/unconstitutional-pizza-delivery-dragnet-slash-failed-ai-research-project/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-06T16:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2013/06/06/unconstitutional-pizza-delivery-dragnet-slash-failed-ai-research-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For this, we&rsquo;ve had our constitutionally-implied right to privacy ignored for the last decade or so:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Cases were referred to by FBI agents as &ldquo;pizza cases&rdquo; because many seemingly suspicious cases turned out to be food takeout orders.</p></p><p><p>[Suspicious Activity ReportS &ndash; SARS, get it?] revealed former New York governor Eliot Spitzer&rsquo;s use of prostitutes, even though he was not suspected of terrorist activities.</p><footer><strong>Wikipedia Editors <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stellar_Wind_">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stellar_Wind_</a>(code_name) code name: Stellar Wind</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><img class="right <a" src="href="http://www.martinoswebster.com/Pictures/pizza.jpg">http://www.martinoswebster.com/Pictures/pizza.jpg</a>" width="712" height="357" title="pizza" ></p>

<p>We could have waited until an anonymized research protocol proved a benefit before having the FBI needlessly harrass politicians mid-pizza-and/or-sperm-delivery: just use some protocol wherein the hashed signatures of identities are compared after terrorists/whatever become known by other means (definitely easy with trusted a third party like the <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/06/confirmed-nsa-spying-millions-americans">EFF</a>, and maybe possible without &ndash; math is magic!). Once we get that false positive rate below 100,000 innocent people per year, then we can talk. Until then, keep that stuff in the AI research community and they&rsquo;ll have something that can play Jeopardy with terrorists within the next few decades. As usual, project leaders with influence push adoption of something useless so they can claim it wasn&rsquo;t all just incremental progress too soon to deploy.</p>

<p>PRISM, on the other hand, may actually provide some benefit now (spying, mostly on those foreigners who don&rsquo;t know they can use encryption):</p>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>The President’s Daily Brief, which cited PRISM data in 1,477 articles last year.</p></p><p><p>When critics of the foreign intelligence statute argued for changes, the only members of Congress who knew about PRISM were bound by oaths of office to hold their tongues.</p></p><p><p>A roster that bears their logos in order of entry into the program: “Microsoft, Yahoo, Google, Facebook, PalTalk, AOL, Skype, YouTube, Apple.” PalTalk, although much smaller, has hosted significant traffic during the Arab Spring and in the ongoing Syrian civil war.</p></p><p><p>Dropbox, the cloud storage and synchronization service, is described as “coming soon.”</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>Gellman and Poitras <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/investigations/us-intelligence-mining-data-from-nine-us-internet-companies-in-broad-secret-program/2013/06/06/3a0c0da8-cebf-11e2-8845-d970ccb04497_story.html">http://www.washingtonpost.com/investigations/us-intelligence-mining-data-from-nine-us-internet-companies-in-broad-secret-program/2013/06/06/3a0c0da8-cebf-11e2-8845-d970ccb04497_story.html</a> code name: PRISM</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>(update: <a href="http://googleblog.blogspot.com/2013/06/what.html">Larry Page denies Google participation</a>)</p>

<p>So what if NSA can only lawfully pursue foreign intelligence? You have the FBI who I&rsquo;m sure are happy to claim a piece of the pie. And rubber stamped warrants have been in plentiful supply of late.</p>

<p>Perhaps Dropbox can add another 250mb free storage each time the government rifles through your My Little Pony porno stash.</p>

<p><blockquote><p></p></p><p><p>An order from the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court (or FISC) directs Verizon to provide “on an ongoing daily basis” all call records for any call “wholly within the United States, including local telephone calls” and any call made “between the United States and abroad.”</p></p><p><p></p><footer><strong>Glenn Greenwald <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/06/confirmed-nsa-spying-millions-americans">https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/06/confirmed-nsa-spying-millions-americans</a> EFF summary of Glenn Greenwald&rsquo;s report</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>So, everything they can get their hands on.</p>

<p>It makes sense that people want to use this info, for what they think are very good reasons. Yet I&rsquo;m not sure &ldquo;let everyone have access to the Panopticon, then we&rsquo;ll watch the watchers&rdquo; is exactly where we want our society defaults to lie, either. There are things I don&rsquo;t want to know about other people. Perhaps we people should punish those who signed off on this, patriots though they may be. But first, let&rsquo;s try whining really loudly, which amounts to the same thing as voting (namely, moves politicians to make empty promises).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[marginal income tax rate over 100%]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/2012/12/02/marginal-income-tax-rate-over-100/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-02T11:46:52-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/2012/12/02/marginal-income-tax-rate-over-100</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>Pennsylvania poor may be sitting on the edge of marginal income tax rates of infinity percent. The state should at least make sure that getting a raise doesn't result in lower net pay. You can expect locally-optimizing welfare recipients to stay at the edge of one of the cliffs (undeclared income is a way out, but won't reduce payments taken from the public).</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div class="p_embed p_image_embed">
<img alt="Image" src="http://graehl.org/images/2012/12/02/marginal-income-tax-rate-over-100/46127632-image.png">
</div>


<br><p></p>


<div><a href="http://www.aei.org/files/2012/07/11/-alexander-presentation_10063532278.pdf">via</a></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
