<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: health | Science & Fun - Jonathan Graehl]]></title>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/categories/health/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://graehl.org/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-04T04:13:15-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://graehl.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Graehl]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[graehl@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[anti- alternative milk]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/anti-alternative-milk/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-26T13:36:25-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/anti-alternative-milk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve had some raw milk from <a href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/sprouts-farmers-market-culver-city">Sprouts</a> and can&rsquo;t get excited enough about it to pay 3x (for whole milk) and possibly risk severe food poisoning (the chance isn&rsquo;t high, but the severity can be).<p></p></p>

<div>
<a href="http://www.kitchenstewardship.com/2010/06/23/the-real-story-of-homogenized-milk-powdered-milk-skim-milk-and-oxidized-cholesterol/">This woman's investigation</a> deflates many pro-raw claims (her method is to ask experts and industry representatives, which seems solid):</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<blockquote style="padding: 0px 0px 0px 10px; margin: 0px 30px 1.5em; font-family: Georgia,Times New Roman,Times,serif; color: rgb(85,85,85); border-left-width: 1px; border-left-style: solid; border-left-color: rgb(170,170,170); font-size: 14px; line-height: 23px; text-align: left; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> <p style="padding: 0px; margin: 0px 0px 1.5em;">Homogenization is done by forcing milk through a small geometry valve at very high pressures (1500-2500 psi).  The effect of this treatment is to break the natural fat globule (average size ~10 micrometers) into  much smaller fat globules (average size  </p>
<p style="padding: 0px; margin: 0px 0px 1.5em;">Within the first 10-20 seconds after homogenization, proteins and segments of the original membrane form a new membrane on the surface of the smaller fat globules.  The addition of the protein to the surface of the fat globules and the reduction in the size of the globules results in the reduction in the ability of the globules to float to the top of the milk.  During this process, the milkfat is not exposed to air as the process is done in an air tight system containing only milk.  Milkfat is made up of 98% triglycerides, which are extremely stable to changes during processing.  The only way that milk will spoil faster after homogenization is if the homogenizing system is not properly cleaned and sanitized.</p> <p style="padding: 0px; margin: 0px 0px 1.5em;">Another factor that may be thrown out is the xanthine oxidase.  Dr. K. Oster proposed a theory in 1971 that xanthine oxidase released from the milk fat globule membrane during homogenization was a contributor to atherosclerosis.  To this end, I would have you read the <a href="http://www.ajcn.org/cgi/content/abstract/38/2/327" rel="nofollow" target="_blank" style="padding: 0px; margin: 0px; color: rgb(51,51,51);">following review article</a>.</p> <p style="padding: 0px; margin: 0px 0px 1.5em;">There is not much if any support for this theory but a lot of people are still using it to scare customers into paying higher prices for cream-line milk.</p>
</blockquote>
<p style="padding: 0px; margin: 0px 0px 1.5em; color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Georgia,Times New Roman,Times,serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 23px; text-align: left; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> Dr. Partridge drinks homogenized store milk himself, although he said he has to take the jugs from the back to avoid the “light oxidized flavor that is prevalent in milk stored under direct fluorescent lighting.” This is not a man who drinks milk without consciousness.</p> </blockquote>


<div>Her thinking seems high quality (although she's in-your-face Christian). Recommended. </div>


<p></p>


<div>If there's anything scary in your cow's diet (I wish I could get grass-fed cow milk easily), it will likely be in the fats, she points out. So cheap skim milk mixed with high quality cream makes sense.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[lithium helps you get up in the morning]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/lithium-helps-you-get-up-in-the-morning/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-26T12:47:53-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/lithium-helps-you-get-up-in-the-morning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.readability.com/read?url=http%3A//www.psmag.com/health/researchers-crack-codes-for-lithium-electroshock-42273/">This article</a> claims as advance in the understanding of why <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithium_pharmacology">lithium helps protect the brain</a>. It turns out that it&rsquo;s at least partially due to forcing sleep. Insufficient sleep is extremely harmful:<p></p></p>

<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<p style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Droid Serif,Droid Sans,sans-serif; font-size: 16px; line-height: 22px; margin: 0px; padding: 0px 0px 15px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> by blocking the enzyme known as glycogen synthase kinase, or GSK3, lithium boosts the master clock’s strength threefold.</p>
<p style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Droid Serif,Droid Sans,sans-serif; font-size: 16px; line-height: 22px; margin: 0px; padding: 0px 0px 15px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> Understanding this mechanism, Meng says, companies are already developing drugs that can block GSK3, but which would be unlikely to trigger lithium’s unwelcome effects such as nausea, dry mouth, tremor, weakness and weight gain.</p> </blockquote>


<p></p>


<div>Now that a mechanism is known, perhaps new patentable synthetics that target just that mechanism, but with slightly different side effects, can provide a $billions cash cow. Lithium was probably underprescribed by the medical industry due to lack of financial incentive.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>I'd started low dose (1mg/day) lithium on the basis of a <a href="http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:YNH35x005wAJ:www.medicineispersonal.com/contest/1st+&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=us">literature review by Scott Siskind</a> on <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/a60/quantified_health_prize_results_announced/">LessWrong</a> and couldn't tell if it was only another nice multivitamin-like placebo, but I may have been sleeping and waking slightly better. Side effects were completely nonexistent for me at 1mg/day. An ordinary diet already supplies .5-3mg/day, though:</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;"><span style="font-family: Arial,Helvetica,sans-serif; line-height: 19px; text-align: justify; background-color: rgb(247,247,248);">In 1985, the EPA, estimated that the daily lithium consumption for a 154 lb. adult ranges from 650 to 3,100 micrograms</span></blockquote>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>Lithium definitely decreases suicides. That's something. There are other claims of decent strength: <a href="http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2010/07/lithium-and-inflammation.html">http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2010/07/lithium-and-inflammation.html</a> and <a href="http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2011/02/lithium-and-longevity.html">http://evolutionarypsychiatry.blogspot.com/2011/02/lithium-and-longevity.html</a>.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>It's suspicious to me when a medicine does so many seemingly different good things. But since the mechanism at least involves sleep, which is central, it's plausible. Also, there are other medicines (aspirin) that really do have several good effects (I assume because excess inflammation can be harmful in many different ways). It's suspicious to me when something has many good effects (speeds/slows several different natural chemical reactions) and no bad effects. I'd expect most tweaks to be only situationally good, or else it's just an accident that evolution hasn't stumbled upon and widely disseminated the capability to produce something analogous to the drug.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[jordan]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/jordan/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-24T21:55:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/jordan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p>


<div class="p_embed p_image_embed">
<img alt="Aaa31" src="http://graehl.org/images/2012/05/24/jordan/41433844-aaa31.jpg">
</div>




<p>Did basketball have a doping era? Talent + obsessive work ethic will get you a long way *if* you have enhanced physical recovery. Maybe that's sometimes purely genetic. Kobe looked pretty buff for a few years post-Shaq (but not unbelievably so). Jordan was never huge but there's more to chemically enhanced performance than bodybuilder physique (which hardly comes without specifically trying).</p>


<p></p>


<div>Why would an athlete *not* dope, especially if they felt it was long-term healthy and unlikely to be detected?</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[red meat may be harmful]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/red-meat-may-be-harmful/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-09T21:29:48-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/red-meat-may-be-harmful</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div>Red meat correlates with death.</div>


<p></p>


<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<span style="color: rgb(51,51,51); font-family: Trebuchet MS,Verdana,Arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; line-height: 18px; text-align: left; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">The researchers carefully controlled</span><span style="color: rgb(51,51,51); line-height: 18px; text-align: left; background-color: rgb(255,255,255); font-family: verdana,arial,helvetica,sans-serif; font-size: x-small;"> <span style="font-size: small;"><span style="font-family: Times,Times New Roman,serif;">for intakes of total energy, whole grains, fruits, and vegetables; age; body mass index; race (white or nonwhite); smoking status</span><span style="font-family: Times,Times New Roman,serif;">; alcohol intake; physical activity level; multivitamin use; aspirin use; family history of diabetes mellitus, myocardial infarction, or cancer; and baseline history of diabetes mellitus, hypertension, or hypercholesterolemia. In women, they also adjusted the data for postmenopausal status and menopausal hormone use.</span></span></span>
</blockquote>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>Seems reasonably solid.</div>


<p></p>


<div>There are plenty of possible causal mechanisms, detailed <a href="http://donmatesz.blogspot.com/2012/04/harvard-meat-study.html">here</a>. Still no proof of overall causality, but it's enough evidence to encourage moderation.</div>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div>Things cooked at high heat (fried, well done, BBQed) are probably additionally unhealthy. </div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[loss of brain matter with age (non-AD)]]></title>
    <link href="http://graehl.org/blog/loss-of-brain-matter-with-age-non-ad/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-07T23:19:13-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://graehl.org/blog/loss-of-brain-matter-with-age-non-ad</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="p_embed p_image_embed">
<img alt="G10" src="http://graehl.org/images/2012/04/07/loss-of-brain-matter-with-age-non-ad/39852194-g10.jpg">
</div>


<p></p>


<div>Disgusting stuff. My poor brain!</div>


<div> </div>


<blockquote class="gmail_quote" style="margin: 0px 0px 0px 0.8ex; border-left-width: 1px; border-left-color: rgb(204,204,204); border-left-style: solid; padding-left: 1ex;">
<span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">brain cell death (both neuronal and glial) is a process that begins at ~ 2 years of age – at least for the neurons that comprise the gray matter of the cerebral cortex, and which proceeds relentlessly throughout the individual’s lifetime (</span><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2896477/?tool=pubmed" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(17,85,204); font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">Giorgio, 2010</a><span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">) Brain cell loss and degeneration become morphologically apparent in the brain’s white matter by the time we are in our early 20’s, although there is evidence that more subtle changes have been afoot for much longer. (</span><a href="http://www.nmr.mgh.harvard.edu/~bradd/gabrieli_2004_nrn1323.pdf" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(17,85,204); font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">Hedden, 2004</a><span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">) Losses in gray matter volume proceed approximately</span><em style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> linearly</em><span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> with age in normal aging, and the average gray matter volume decreases from ~390 mL at age 22, to ~300 ml at age 82. (</span><a href="http://radiology.rsna.org/content/216/3/672.long" target="_blank" style="color: rgb(17,85,204); font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">Courchesne, 2000</a><span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">) Total loss in brain mass between age 20 and age 80 is, on average, ~450 g, or roughly 1/3</span><sup style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);">rd</sup><span style="font-family: arial,sans-serif; font-size: 13px; background-color: rgb(255,255,255);"> of our youthful brain volume.</span>
</blockquote>


<p> <p></p></p>

<div><a href="http://chronopause.com/index.php/2012/04/06/much-less-than-half-a-chance-part-5/">via</a></div>


<p></p>


<div>White matter peaks at 30 and declines slowly, though (note: the graphs are of different individuals at different ages; changes could also be due to generational environmental differences, perhaps).</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
